<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A review of the seditious pamphlet lately pnblished [sic] in Holland by Dr. Bramhell, pretended Bishop of London-Derry; entitled, His faire warning against the Scots discipline. In which, his malicious and most lying reports, to the great scandall of that government, are fully and clearly refuted. As also, the Solemne League and Covenant of the three nations justified and maintained. / By Robert Baylie, minister at Glasgow, and one of the commissioners from the Church of Scotland, attending the King at the Hague.</title>
            <author>Baillie, Robert, 1599-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E563_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858870</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858870</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110929</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77478)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110929)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 87:E563[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A review of the seditious pamphlet lately pnblished [sic] in Holland by Dr. Bramhell, pretended Bishop of London-Derry; entitled, His faire warning against the Scots discipline. In which, his malicious and most lying reports, to the great scandall of that government, are fully and clearly refuted. As also, the Solemne League and Covenant of the three nations justified and maintained. / By Robert Baylie, minister at Glasgow, and one of the commissioners from the Church of Scotland, attending the King at the Hague.</title>
                  <author>Baillie, Robert, 1599-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64 [i.e. 71], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Mich. Stait, dwelling at the Turf-Market,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Delph :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to Bramhall, John.  Fair warning to take heed of the Scotish discipline.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 5th".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and the Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bramhall, John, 1594-1663. --  Fair warning to take heed of the Scotish discipline.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643).</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110929:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110929:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REVIEVV OF THE Seditious Pamphlet lately publiſhed in HOLLAND by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Brambell,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Biſhop of <hi>London-Derry;</hi> ENTITLED, <hi>His faire Warning againſt the</hi> SCOTS DISCIPLINE.</p>
            <p>In which, His malicious and moſt lying Reports, to the great ſcandall of that Government, are fully and clearly refuted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo,</hi> The Solemne League and Covenant of the three Nations juſtified and maintained.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Baylie,</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> and one of the Commiſſioners from the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> attending the KING at the <hi>Hague.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Delph</hi> by <hi>Mich. Stait,</hi> dwelling at the Turf-Market. 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:110929:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110929:2"/>
            <head>For the Right Honourable the Noble and Potent Lord, <hi>John</hi> Earle of <hi>Caſſils,</hi> Lord <hi>Kennedy,</hi> &amp;c. one of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Privy-Counſell, and Lord Iuſtice generall of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y long experience of your Lordſhips ſincere zeale to the truth of God, and affection to the liberties of the Church and Kingdome of Scotland, againſt all enemies whomſoever, hath emboldened me to offer by your Lordſhips hand to the view of the publick, my following anſwer to a very bitter enemy of that Church and Kingdome, for their adherence to the ſacred truth of God, and their owne juſt Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t es.</p>
            <p>At my firſt ſight of his Book, and many days thereafte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">The Authors reaſons of his writing.</note> I had no purpoſe at all to meddle with him: your Lordſhip knowes how unprovided men of my preſent condition muſt be, either with leiſure, or accommodations, or a mind ſuitable for writing of Books. Alſo Doctor <hi>Bramble</hi> was ſo well knowne on the other ſide of the Sea, the juſtice of the Parliament of England and Scotland having unanimouſly condemned him to ſtand upon the higgeſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of infamy, among the firſt of the unpardonable incendiaries, and in the head of the moſt pernicious inſtruments of the late miſeries in Britaine and Ireland: and the evident falſhood of his calumnies were ſo clearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed long ago in printed Anſwers to the Infamous Authors whence he had borrowed them. I ſaw laſtly the mans ſpirit ſo extreme ſaucy, and his pen ſo waſpiſh and full of gall, that I judged him unworthy of any anſwer. But underſtanding his malicious boldneſſe to put his Booke in the hand of His Majeſty, of the Prince of Orange, and all the eminent Perſonages of this place, who can read Engliſh; yea to ſend it abroad unto all the Univerſities of theſe Provinces, with very high and inſinuating commendations, from the prime favourers of the Epiſcopall cauſe: hearing alſo the threats of that faction to put this their excellent and unanſwerable peece, both in Dutch, French, and Latine; that in the whole neighbouring World the reputation of the Scots might thereby be wounded, killed, and buried, without hope of recovery; I found it neceſſary, at the deſire of divers friends, to ſend this my review after it, hoping that all who ſhall be pleaſed to be at the paines of comparing the Reply with the challenge, may be induced to pronounce him not only a raſh, untimous, malicious, but alſo a very falſe accuſer. This much juſtice doe I expect from every judicious and equitable comparer of our wrytes, upon the hazard of their cenſure to fall upon my ſide.<note place="margin">The Prelate are unable by reaſon to defend E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy.</note>
            </p>
            <p>His invectives againſt us are chiefly for three things, our Diſcipline, our Covenant, our alleaged unkindnes to our late Soveraigne. My apology for the firſt, is, that in diſcipline we maintaine no conſiderable concluſion, but
<pb facs="tcp:110929:3"/> what is avowed by all the Reformed Churches, eſpecially our Brethren of Holland and France, as by the approbatory ſuffrages of the Univerſitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Leyden, Utrecht and others, to the theorems whereupon our adverſary doth build his chiefe accuſations, may appeare. If our practiſe had aberred fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the common rule, the crookedneſſe of the one ought not to prejudge the ſtraitneſſe of the other: though what our adverſary alleadgeth of theſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>errations is nothing, but his owne calumnious imputations: the chiefe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell is our rule it ſelf, which all the Reformed harmoniouſly defend with us, to be according to Scripture; and the Epiſcopall declinations, to be beſide and againſt the line of the word, yea Antichriſtian.</p>
            <p>If our Prelates had found the humor of diſputing this maine cauſe to ſtir in their veines, why did they not vent it in replyes to <hi>Didoclavius,</hi> and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Bucerus,</hi> who for long thirty years have ſtood unanſwered? or if freſher meats had more pleaſed their taſt, why did not their ſtomacks venture on <hi>Salmaſius</hi> or <hi>Blondels</hi> books againſt Epiſcopacy? If verball debates had liked them better than writing, why had none of them the courage to accept the conference, with that incomparably moſt learned of all Knights now living, or in any bygone age Sir <hi>Claud Somayis,</hi> who by a perſon of honour about the King did ſignifie his readineſſe to prove before His Majeſty, againſt any one, or all his Prelaticall Divines, that their Epiſcopacy had no warrant at all in the word of God, or any good reaſon?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Their ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are tricks of Court.</note>But our friends are much wiſer then to be at the trouble and hazard of any ſuch exerciſe; the artifices of the Court are their old trade, they know better how to watch the ſeaſons, and to diſtribute amongſt themſelves the houres of the Kings opportunities, when privately without contradiction they may inſtill in his tender mind their corrupt principles, and inſtruct him in his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine, how ſafe it is for his conſcience, and how much for his honor, rather to ruine himſelf, his Family, and all his Kingdoms, with his own hands, then to deſert the holy Church, that is, the Biſhops and their followers; then to joyne with the rebellious Covenanters, enemies to God, to his Father, to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy that the embracing of the barbarous Iriſh, the pardoning of all their monſtrous murders, the rewarding of their expected merits with a free liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Popery, and acceſſe to all places of the higheſt truſt, though contrary to all the Lawes which England and Ireland has known this hundred yeares; all this without and before any Parliament, muſt be very conſiſtent, with conſcience, honour, and all good reaſon. Yea to bind up the ſoule of the moſt ſweet and ingenuous of Princes, in the chaines of their ſlavery for ever, they have fallen upon a moſt rare tricke, which hardly the inventions of all their Predeceſſors can paralell. They reſt not ſatisfied, that for the uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their ambition and greed,<note place="margin">The Biſhops unlucky foot is viſible in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they did harden our late Soveraigne to his very laſt in their Errours, and without compaſſion did drive him on to his fatall praecipice; unleſſe they make him continue after his death to cry loud every day in the eares of his Sonne in his later will and teſtament, to follow him in that ſame way of ruine; rather than to give over to ſerve the luſts of the Prelaticall Clergy. They have gathered together His Majeſties laſt papers, and out of them have made a Booke, whereupon their beſt pens
<pb facs="tcp:110929:3"/> have dropped the greateſt eloqution, reaſon and devotion was among them, by way of eſſayes; as it were to frame the heart of the Son by the fingers of the dying Father to piety, wiſedome, patience, and every virtue; but ever and anon to let fall ſo much of their owne ungracious dew, as may irrigat the ſeeds of their prelaticall Errors and Church intereſt; ſo farre as to charge him to preſevere in the maintainance of Epiſcopall governement upon all hazards, without the change of any thing except a little p. 278. and to aſſure that all Covenanters are of a faction engaged into a Religious rebellion, who may never be truſted till they have repented of their Covenant: and that till then never leſſe loyalty juſtice or humanity may be expected from any, then from them; that if he ſtand in need of them hee is undone, for they will devoure him as the Serpent does the dove.</p>
            <p>Theſe and the like pernicious maxims framed by an Epiſcopall hand, of purpoſe to ſeparate for ever the King from all his covenanted ſubjects, how far they were from the heart, language and writings of our late Soveraigne, all who were aquainted with his cariage and moſt intime affections at New-Caſtle in the Iſle of Wight, and thereafter, can teſtify. But it is reaſon when the Prelates do frame an Image of a King that they ſhould have liberty to place their owne image in its forehead, as the ſtatuary of old did his, in the <hi>Boſs</hi> of <hi>Pallas</hi> targe, with ſuch artifice that all her worſhipers were neceſſitat to worſhip him, and that no hand was able to deſtroy the one without the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and breaking in peeces of the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her; yet our Prelats would know, that in this age their be many excellent Engyneers, whoſe witty practicks tranſcend the moſt skilfull experiments of our Aunceſtors: and whatever may be the ignorance or weaknes of men, wee truſt the breath of our Lords mouth will not faile to blow out the Biſhop from the Kings armes, without any detriment at all to royalty. Allwayes the wicked and impious cunning of theſe craftmen is much to be blamed who dare be bold to inſert and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave themſelfes ſo deeply in the images of the Gods as the one cannot be intended to be picked out of the other more then the Aple from the eye, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the ſubſiſtence of both be But in hazard.</p>
            <p>The other matter of his railing againſt us is the ſolemne league and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant;<note place="margin">The only crime of the Covenant, is that it extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate prelacy.</note> when this nimble &amp; quick enough Doctor comes aflicted with all the reaſons the whole Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> can afford him, to demonſtrat it as he ptofeſſes in his laſt Chapter, to be wicked, falſe, void, and what not; we find his moſt demonſtrative proofs to be ſo poore and ſilly that they infer nothing of his concluſion. To this day no man has ſhewed any errour in the matter of that covenant; as for our, framing and taking of it, our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries drave us thereunto, with a great deale of neceſſity, and now being in it, neither their fraud nor force may bring us from it againe; for we feare the oath of God. After much deliberation we found that covenant the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne meanes to joyne and keep together the whole orthodox party in the three Kingdomes, for the defence of their Religion and liberties, which a popiſh, prelaticall and malignant faction with al their might were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning, who ſtill to this day are going on in the ſame deſigne, without any viſible change, in the moſt of their former principles. And why ſhould any
<pb facs="tcp:110929:4"/> who loves the King hate this covenant, which is the ſtrayteſtry the world can deviſe, to knit all to him and his poſterity, if ſo be his <hi>Majeſty</hi> might be pleaſed to enter therein? but by all meanes ſuch a miſchief muſt be aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for ſo the root of Epiſcopacy would quickly wither without any hope of repullulation; an evill far greater in the thoughts of them who now mannage the conſcience of the Court, then the extirpation of Monarchy, the everſion of all the three Kingdomes, or any other earthly miſery.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Biſhops are moſt juſtly caſt out of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note>As for the third ſubject of the Warners fury againſt us, our unkindnes to the late King, if any truth were in this falſe challenge, no other creature on earth could be ſuppoſed the true cauſe thereof, but our unhappy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats: all our grievances both of Church and Sate, firſt and laſt, came princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally from them: had they never been authors of any more miſchief, then what they occaſioned to our late Soveraigne, his perſon, family and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions this laſt dozen of yeares, there is abundant reaſon of burying that their praeter and Antiſcripturall order in the grave of perpetuall infamy. But the truth is, beſide more ancient quarrels, ſince the dayes of our fathers the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> this limb of Antichriſt has ever been witneſſed againſt; <hi>Wickliſe, Huſs,</hi> and their followers were zealous in this charge, till <hi>Luther</hi> and his diſciples got it flung out of all the reformed world, except England; where the violence of the ill-adviſed princes did keep it up for the perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all trouble of that land, till now at laſt it hath well neer kicked downe to the ground there both Church and Kingdome.<note place="margin">The Scots were never injurious to their King.</note> As for the point in hand, we deny all unkindnes to our King whereof any reaſonable complaint can be framed againſt us. Our firſt conteſts ſtand juſtified this day by King and Parliament in both Kingdomes. When his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> was ſo ill adviſed as to bring down upon our borders an Engliſh army for to puniſh our refuſing of a world of novations in our Religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> contrary to the laws of God and of our country, what could our land doe leſſe then lie down in their armes upon Dunce law for their juſt and neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry defence? when it was in their power with eaſe to have diſſipat the oppoſite army, they ſhew themſelves moſt ready upon very eaſy conditions to goe home in peace, and gladly would have reſted there, had not the furious Biſhops moved his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> without all provocation, to break the firſt peace and make for a ſecond invaſion of Scotland, only to ſecond their unreaſonable rage: was it not then neceſſary for the Scots to arme againe? when they had defeat the Epiſcopall Army and taken New-caſtle, though they found nothing conſiderable to ſtand in their way to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, yet they were content to lie ſtill in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and upon very meane tearms to return the ſecond time in peace. For all this the Prelats could not give it over, but raiſed a new Army and filled England with fire and ſword, yea well neere ſubdued the Parliament and their followers, and did almoſt accompliſh their firſt deſignes upon the whole Iſle. The Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> then with moſt earneſt and pitifull entreaties were called upon by their Brethren of England for helpe, where unwilling that their brethren ſhould periſh in their ſight, and a bridge ſhould be made over their carcaſſes for a third warre upon Scotland, when after long triall they had found all their interceſſions with the King for a modern and reaſonable accomodation
<pb facs="tcp:110929:4"/> ſlighted and rejected, they ſuffered themſelves to be perſwaded to enter co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with their oppreſſed and fainting brethren, for the mantainance of the common cauſe of Religion and liberty, but with expreſſe Articles for the preſervation of royalty in all its juſt rights in his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and his poſterity; what unkindnes was here in the Scots to their King?</p>
            <p>When by Gods bleſſing on the Scots helpe the oppoſite faction was fully ſubdued, his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> left <hi>Oxford</hi> with a purpoſe for <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Scots ſelling of the King is a moſt falſe calumnie.</note> but by the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ordinances againſt his receivers, he diverted towards <hi>Linn,</hi> to ſhip for <hi>Holland</hi> or <hi>France;</hi> where by the way fearing a diſcovery and ſurpriſe, he was neceſſitate to caſt himſelfe upon the Scots army at <hi>New-wark;</hi> upon his promiſe to give ſatisfaction to the propoſitions of both Kingdomes, he was received there and came with them to <hi>New-caſtle:</hi> here his old oaths to adhaere unto Epiſcopacy hindred him to give the expected ſatisfaction. At that time the prime leaders of the Engliſh army were ſeeking with all earneſtnes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to fall upon the Scots, much out of heart and reputation by <hi>Iames Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hame</hi> and his <hi>Irishes</hi> incurſions, moſt unhappy for the Kings affaires: Scotland at that time was ſo full of diviſions, that if the King had gone thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were in an evident hazard of a preſent war both within among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfs, and without from England: our friends in the Engliſh Parliament whom we did, and had reaſon to truſt, aſſured us that our taking the King with us to Scotland, was the keeping of the Sectarian Army on foot, for the wrack of the King, of Scotland, of the Presbyterian party in England; as the ſending of his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> to one of his houſes neer London, upon the faith of the Parliament of England, was the onely way to get the Sectaryes diſarmed, the King and the people ſettled in a peace, upon ſuch tearmes as ſhould be ſatisfactory both to the King and the Scots and all the wel-affected in England. This being the true caſe, was it any, either unjuſtice, unkindnes or imprudence in the Scots to leave the King with his Parliment of England? was this a ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of him to his enemyes? the monys the Scots received at their departure out of England had no relation at all to the King, they were ſcarce the ſixth parte of the arreares due to them for bygon ſervice; they were but the one halfe of the ſum capitulat for, not only without any reference to the King, but by an act of the Engliſh Parliament excluding expreſly from that Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the armies departure all conſideration of the diſpoſall of the Kings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The unexpected evills that followed in the Armyes rebellion in their ſeaſing on London, deſtroying the Parliament, murthering the King, no mortall eye could have forſeen. The Scots were ever ready to the utmoſt of their power to have prevented all theſe miſchiefes with the hazard of what was deareſt to them; notwithſtanding of all the hard meaſure they had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten received both from the King and the moſt of their friends in England. That they did not in time and unanimouſly ſtur to purpoſe for theſe ends, they are to anſwer it to God, who were the true Authors; the innocency of the Church is cleered in the following treatiſe. Among the many cauſes of theſe miſeries the prime fountaine was the venome of Epiſcopall principles which ſome ſerpents conſtantly did infuſe by their ſpeaches and letters in the cares and heart of the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o keep him off from giving that ſatisfaction to
<pb facs="tcp:110929:5"/> his good ſubjects which they found moſt neceſſary and due; the very ſame cauſe which ties up this day the hands of covenanters from redreſſing all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent miſorders could they have the King to joyne with them in their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to quit his unhappy Biſhops, to lay aſide his formall and dead Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, to caſt himſelfe upon the counſels of his Parliaments it were eaſy to prophecie what quickly would become of all his enemies: but ſo long as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall and malignant agents compaſſeth him about (though al that comes neer may ſee him as lovely, hopefull, and promiſing a prince for all naturall endowements as this day breaths in Europe, or for a long time has ſwayed a Scepter in Britaine) yet while ſuch unlucky birds neſt in his Cabin, and men ſo ungraciouſly principled doe daily beſiege him, what can his good people doe but ſit downe with mournfull eyes and bleeding hearts, till the Lord amend theſe otherwiſe remediles and inſuperable evils? but I hold here leſt I tranſgreſſe to farr the bounds of an Epiſtle</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſon off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note>I count it an advantage to have you Lordſhip my judge in what here and in my following treatiſe, I ſpeak of Religion, the liberties of our country and the Royall Family: I know none fitter then your Lordſhip, both to diſcerne and decerne in all theſe matters. Me thinks I may ſay it without flattery (which I never much loved either; in my ſelf or others) that among all our Nobles for conſtancy in a zealous profeſſion, for exemplary practiſe in publick and privat duties, the mercie of God has given to your Lordſhip a reputation ſecond to none. And for a rigid adhaerence to the Rights and Priviledges of your Country, according to that auncient diſpoſition of your Noble Family, noted in our Hiſtorians, eſpecially that Prince of them <hi>George Buchanan,</hi> the Tutor of your <hi>Grand-Father,</hi> I know none in our Land who will pretend to go before you; and for the affaires of the King, your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of blood in the Royall Family is ſo well known, that it would be a ſtrange impudency in me, if in your audience I durſt be bold wittingly to give finiſtrous information. Praying to God that what in the candid inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity and true zeale of my ſpirit, I preſent under your Lordſhips patrociny unto the eye of the World, for the vindication of my mother Church and Country, from the Sicophantick accuſations of a Stigmatiſed incendiary, may produce the intended effects.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I reſt your Lordſhips in all Chriſtian duty, <hi>R. B. G.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Hague <date>this 28 <hi>May</hi>/7 <hi>June.</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110929:5"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Prelaticall faction continue reſolute, that the King and all His People ſhall periſh, rather then the Prelats, not reſtored to former places of Power, for to ſet up Popery, Profanity, and Tyranny, in all the three Kingdoms.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hile the Commiſſioners of the Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Scotland,<note place="margin">The unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſſe of D. Brambles writing.</note> were on their way make their firſt addreſſes to his Majeſty, for to condole his moſt lamentable afflictions, and to make offer of their beſt affections and ſervices for his comfort, in this time of his great diſtreſſe; it was the wiſdom and charity of the Prelaticall party, to ſend out <hi>Doctor Bramble,</hi> to meet them with his Faire Warning. For what elſe? but to diſcourage them in in the very entry from tendering their propoſitions, and before they were ever heard, to ſtop his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties eares with grievous prejudice, againſt all that poſſibly they could ſpeak; though the world ſees that the onely apparent fountain of hope upon earth, for the recovery of the wofully confounded affaires of the King, is in the hands of that Anti-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall Nation: but it is the hope of theſe who love the welfare of the KING and the people, of the Churches and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of Britain, that the hand of God which hath broken all the former devices of the Prelats, ſhall cruſh this their engine alſo.</p>
            <p>Our warner undertaketh to oppugne the Scots diſcipline in a way of his own, none of the moſt rationall,<note place="margin">The irationall way of the Warners wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> He does not ſo much as pretend to ſtate a queſtion, nor in his whole Book to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any main poſition of his oppoſites, either Scripture, Father or reaſon, nor ſo much as aſſay to anſwer any one of their argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt Epiſcopacy; only he culs out ſome of their by-te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, belonging little or nothing to the main queſtions, and from them takes occaſion to gather together in a heap all the calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies which of old, or of late their known enemies out of the forge of their malice and fraud, did obtrude on the credulity of ſimple people: alſo ſome decorted paſſages from the books of their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110929:6"/> friends, to bring the way of that Church into deteſtation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any juſt reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The moſt of his ſtuffe is borrowed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong ago con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</note>Theſe practiſes in our Warner are the leſs pardonable, that though he knows the chief of his allegations, to bee but borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from his late much beloved Comrades Maſter <hi>Corbet</hi> in his <hi>Lyſimachus Nicanor,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Maxwel</hi> in his <hi>Iſſachart Burden,</hi> yet he was neither deterred by the ſtrange puniſhments, which God from heaven inflicted viſibly on both theſe Calumniators of their Mother Church, nor was pleaſed in his repeating of their calumnious arguments, to releeve any of them from the excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under the which they ſtand publickly confuted, I ſuppoſe to his own diſtinct knowledge, I know certainly, to the open view of thouſands in Scotland, England and Ireland; but it makes for the Warners deſign to diſſemble here in Holland, that ever he heard of ſuch Books as <hi>Lyſimachus Nicanor,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſſachars Burden,</hi> much leſſe of Maſter <hi>Baylies Anſwer</hi> to both, Printed ſome years agoe at <hi>London, Edenburg</hi> and <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> without a rejoynder from any of that faction to this day.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions bitternes of the Warners ſpirit.</note>However let our Warner be heard. In the very firſt page of his firſt chapter, we may taſt the ſweetneſſe of his meek Spirit: at the very entry, he concludeth but without any pretence to an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there or elſe where, <hi>the diſcipline of the Church of Scotland to be their own invention, whereon they dote, the Diana, which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have canonized, their own dreams, the counterfeit image which they faine hath fallen down from Jupiter, which they ſo much adore, the very quinteſſence of refined Popery, not only moſt injurious to the civil Magiſtrate, moſt oppreſſive to the Subject, moſt pernicious to both; but alſo incenſiſtent with all forms of civil Government, deſtructive to all ſorts of Policy, a rack to the conſcience, the heavieſt preſſure that can fall on a people.</hi> So much truth and ſoberneſſe doth the Warner breath out in his very firſt page.</p>
            <p>Though he had no regard at all to the cleer paſſages of Holy Scripture, whereupon the Scots do build their Anti-Epiſcopall tenets; nor any reference to the harmony of the reformed Churches, which unanimouſly joyn with the Scots in the main of their Diſcipline, eſpecially in that which the Doctor hates moſt therein, the rejection of Epiſcopacy: yet methinks ſome little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect might have appeared in the man to the Authority of the Magiſtrate, and civill Laws, which are much more ingeminated by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110929:6"/> this worthy Divine over all his book, then the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Can be ſo ſoon forget that the whole diſcipline of the Church of Scotland, as it is there taught and practiſed,<note place="margin">The Warner ſtricks at the Scots Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline through the Kings ſides.</note> is eſtabliſhed by Acts of Parliament, and hath all the ſtrength which the King and State can give to a civill Law? the Warner may well be grieved, but hardly can he be ignorant, that the Kings Majeſty at this day does not at all queſtion the juſtice of theſe ſanctions: what ever therefore be the Doctors thoughts, yet ſo long as he pretends to keep upon his face the mask of loyalty, he muſt be content to eat his former words, yea, to burn his whole book: otherwiſe he layes againſt his own profeſſions, a ſlander upon the King, and His Royal Father, of great ignorance, or huge injuſtice, the one having eſtabliſhed, the other offring to eſtabliſh by their civil laws, a Church Diſcipline for the whole Nation of Scotland, which truly is the quinteſſence of Popery, pernicious and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to all formes of civil Government, and the heavieſt preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that can fall upon a people.</p>
            <p>All the cauſe of of this choler which the Warner is pleaſed to ſpeak out, is the attempt of the Scots,<note place="margin">In the threſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold he ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles on the Kings conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> to obtrude their Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline upon the King, contrary to the dictats of his own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to compell forraign Churches to embrace the ſame. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is it not preſumption in our warner, ſo ſoon to tell the world in print what are the dictats of the Kings conſcience, as yet he is not his Majeſties confeſſor, and if the Clerk of the Cloſet had whiſpered ſomewhat in his care, what he heard in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, he ought not to have proclaimed it without a warrant; but we do altogether miſtruſt his reports of the Kings conſcience: for who will beleeve him, that a knowing and a juſt King will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be content, to command and impoſe on a whole Nation by his laws, a diſcipline contrary to the dictats of his own conſcience. This great ſtumble upon the Kings conſcience in the firſt page, muſt be an ominous ceſpitation on the threſhold.</p>
            <p>The other imputation hath no juſt ground:<note place="margin">The Scots ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver offered to impoſe any thing upon England.</note> the Scots did never meddle, to impoſe upon forraign Churches, there is queſtion of none, but the Engliſh; and the Scots were never ſo preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as to impoſe any thing of theirs upon that Church. It was the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> convocat by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of England, which after long deliberation, and much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, unanimouſly concluded the Presbyterian. Diſcipline in all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110929:7"/> the parts therof, to be agreable to the word of God: it was the two Houſes of the Parliament of England without a contrary voice, who did ordaine the abolition of Epiſcopacy, and the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of Presbyteries and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynods in England and Ireland. Can here the Scots be ſaid to compell the Engliſh to dance after their pipe, when their own Aſſembly of Divines begins the ſong, when the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land concurre without a diſordering opinion, when the King himſelf for perfecting the harmony offers, to add his voice for three whole years together?</p>
            <p>In the remainder of the Chapter the warner layes upon the Scots three other crimes: Firſt, That they count it Eraſtianiſme to put the Government of the Church in the hand of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ.</hi> The Doctors knowledg is greater then to be ignorant, that all theſe goe under the name of tne Eraſtians,<note place="margin">The elder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d were E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtians, and more, but the younger are as much anti-E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtian as the moſt rigid of the Presbytery.</note> who walking in Eraſtus ways of flattering the Magiſtrate, to the prejudice of the juſt rights of the Church, run yet out beyond Eraſtus perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall tenets; I doubt if that man went ſo far as the Doctor here and elſewhere, to make all Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction, but a part of the Magiſtrats civill power, which for its Execution, the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governours of any ſtate may derive out of the fountain of their ſupremacy to what ever hands civill or eccleſiaſtick them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves think fit to commit it. Let the Doctor adde to this much knowledge, but a little ingenuity, and he ſhall confeſſe, that his brethren the latter Biſhops, who claim: Epiſcopacy by Divine Right, are all as much againſt this Eraſtian Ceſaro-papiſme, as any Presbyterian in Scotland. The Elder Biſhops indeed of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and all the Laws there for Epiſcopacy ſeem to be point blank according to the Eraſtian errors: for they make the Crown and Royall Supremacy the originall, root and fountain whence all the iſcipline of the Church did flow: as before the days of Henry the Eight it did out of the Popes headſhip of the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>under Chriſt. However let the Doctor ingeniouſly ſpeak out his ſence, and I am deceived, if he ſhall not acknowledge, that how groſſe an Eraſtian ſo ever himſelf and the eldeſt Biſhops of England might have been, yet that long agoe, the moſt of his prelaticall friends have become as much oppoſite to Eraſtianiſme, as the moſt rigid of the Presbyterians.</p>
            <p>The other crime he layes to the charge of the<note n="*" place="margin">The Scots firſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt crime is irreconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe with Rome.</note> Scots is, that they admit no latitude in Religion, but will have every opinion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110929:7"/> a fundamentall Article of Faith, and are averſe from the reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alition of the Proteſtant Churches. <hi>Anſ.</hi> If the Warner had found it ſeaſonable to vent a little more of his true ſenſe in this point, he had charged this great crime far more home upon the head of the Scots: for indeed, though they were ever far from denying the true degrees of importance, which do cleerly appear among the multitude of Chriſtian truths, yet the great quarrel here of the Warner and his friends againſt them, is, that they ſpoyled the <hi>Canterburian</hi> deſigne of reconciling the Proteſtant Churches, not among themſelves, but with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> When theſe good men were with all earneſtneſs proclaiming the greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of Papiſts and Proteſtants to be upon no fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, but onely diſputable opinions, wherein belief on either ſide was ſafe enough, and when they found that the Papiſts did ſtand punctually to the Tenets of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately unwilling to come over to <hi>England,</hi> their great labour was, that the Engliſh, and the reſt of the Proteſtants, caſting aſide their needleſs belief of problematick truths, in piety, charity and zeal, to make up the breach, and take away the ſchiſm, ſhould be at all the pains to make the journey to <hi>Rome.</hi> While this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne is far advanced, and furiouſly driven on in all the three Kingdoms, and by none more in <hi>Ireland</hi> then the Biſhop of <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> behold, the rude and plain Blue-caps ſtep in to the play, and mar all the Game: By no art, by no terrour can theſe be gotten along to ſuch a reconciliation. This was the firſt and greateſt crime of the Scots, which the Doctor here glances at, but is ſo wiſe and modeſt a man as not to bring it above board.</p>
            <p>The laſt charge of the chapter is, that the Scots<note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> were ever anti-epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal.</note> keep not ſtill that reſpect to the Biſhops of <hi>England,</hi> which they were wont of old in the beginning of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign. <hi>Anſ.</hi> In that Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cited by the Warner from the general Aſſembly of <hi>Scotland,</hi> 1566. Seſſ. 3. there is no word of approbation to the Office of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy; they ſpeak to the Biſhops of England in no other qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or relation, but as Miniſters of the word, the higheſt ſtile they give them, is, Reverend Paſtors and Brethren; the tenour of the whole Epiſtle is a grave and brotherly admonition to beware of that fatall concomitant of the moſt moderate Epiſcopacy, the troubling of the beſt and moſt zealous ſervants of Chriſt for idle and fruitleſs Ceremonies. How great a reverence the Church of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110929:8"/> Scotland at that time carried to Prelacy, may be ſeen in their Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the ſecret Councel of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in that ſame Aſſembly the very day and Seſſion wherein they writ the Letter in hand to the Biſhops of <hi>England.</hi> The Arch-biſhp of S. <hi>Andrews</hi> being then uſurping juriſdiction over the Miniſtry by ſome warrant from the State, the Aſſembly was grieved, not only with the Popery of that Biſhop, but with his <hi>ancient juriſdiction,</hi> which in all Biſhops, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh and proteſtant, is one and the ſame: That juriſdiction was the only matter of their preſent complaint; and in relation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, they aſſure the Councel in diſtinct terms, that <hi>they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be more ſubject unto that uſurped Tyranny, then they would be to the Divel himſelf.</hi> So reverend an opinion had the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> at that time of Epiſcopal Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Prelates lately were found in the act of introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Popery in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, and Tyranny into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</note>But ſuppone that ſome fourſcore yeers ago, the Scots, before they had taſted the fruits of Proteſtant Biſhops, had judged them tolerable in <hi>England;</hi> yet ſince that time, by the long tract of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs which conſtantly have accompanied the order of Prelacy, they have been put upon a more accurate inſpection of its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and have found it not onely a needleſſe, but a noxious and poyſonous weed, neceſſary to be plucked up by the root, and caſt over the hedge. Beſide all its former malefices, it hath been deprehended of late in the very act of everting the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, both of Religion and Government, of bringing in Popery and Tyranny in the Churches and States of all the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, (<hi>Canterburian ſelf-conviction, cap.</hi> 1.)</p>
            <p>And for theſe crimes it was condemned, killed, and buried in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the unanimous conſent of King, Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; when <hi>England</hi> thereafter both in their Aſſembly and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, without a diſcording voice, had found it neceſſary to root out that unhappy plant, as long ago with great wiſdom it had been caſt out of all the reſt of the reformed Churches; had not the Scots all the reaſon in the world to applaud ſuch pious, juſt and neceſſary reſolutions of their Engliſh Brethren, though the Warner ſhould call it the greateſt crime?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:110929:8"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Preſbyterians aſſert poſitively the Magiſtrates right to convocate Synods, to confirm their acts, to reform the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches within their Dominions.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN the ſecond Chapter the Warner charges the Scots Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with the overthrowing the Magiſtrates right in convocating of Synods. When he comes to prove this,<note place="margin">No controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in <hi>Scotland</hi> betwixt the King and the Church, about the convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods.</note> he forgets his chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, and digreſſes from it to the Magiſtrates power of chuſing Elders and making Eccleſiaſtick Laws, avowing that theſe things are done in <hi>Scotland</hi> by Eccleſiaſtick perſons alone, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the King or his Councel. <hi>Anſ.</hi> It ſeems, our Warner is very ignorant of the way of the Scots Diſcipline: the ordinary and ſet meetings of all Aſſemblies both Nationall and provinciall ſince the firſt reformation are determined by Acts of Parliament, with the Kings conſent; ſo betwixt the King and the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> there is no queſtion for the convocating of ordinary Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies: for extraordinary, no man in <hi>Scotland</hi> did ever controvert the Kings power, to call them when and where he pleaſed: as for the inherent power of the Church to meet for diſcipline, as well as for worſhip, the warner falls on it hereafter, we muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paſſe it in this place.</p>
            <p>What he means to ſpeak of the Kings power in chuſing Elders or making Eccleſiaſtick Laws, himſelf knows:<note place="margin">The Warners Eraſtian and Tyrannick principles ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the King.</note> his Majeſtie in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> did never require any ſuch priviledge as the election of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or Commiſſioners to Parliament, or members of any incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, civil or eccleſaiſtick, where the Laws did not expreſly provide the nomination to be in the Crown. The making of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick Laws in <hi>England</hi> as well as in as in <hi>Scotland,</hi> was ever with the Kings good contentment, referred to Eccleſiaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies: but the Warner ſeems to be in the mind of thoſe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, who put the power of preaching, of adminiſtring the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and Diſcipline, in the ſupreme Magiſtrate alone, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives it out of him as the Head of the Church, to what Members he thinks expedient to communicate it: alſo that the Legiſlative Power, aſwel in Eccleſiaſtick as civil Affairs, is the property of the King alone. That the Parliaments and general Aſſemblies are but his arbitrary Councels, the one for matters of State, the other
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110929:9"/> for matters of the Church, with whom or without whom hee makes Acts of Parliament and Church-cannons, according to his good pleaſure, that all the Offices of the Kingdom both of Church and State are from him, as he gives a commiſſion to whom he will to be a Sheriff or Juſtice of Peace, ſo he ſends out whom he pleaſeth to preach and celebrate Sacraments by vertue of his Regal miſſion The Warner and his Eraſtian friends may well extend the Royal Supremacy to this largeneſſe, but no King of Scotland was ever willing to accept of ſuch a power though by erroneous flatterers, ſometime obtruded upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m, <hi>(ſe Canterburian ſelf conviction, cap. ult.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Warners ignorant and falſe report of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</note>The warner wil not leave this matter in generall, he diſcends to inſtance a number of particular incroachments of the Scots Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters upon the Royal authority: we muſt diſpence in all his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with a ſmall piccadillo in reaſoning, he muſt be permitted to lay all the faults of the Presbyterians in Scotland upon the back of the Presbytery it ſelf, and if the faylings of Officers were naturall to, and inſeparable from their Office: miſ-kennning this little mote of unconſequentiall argumenting, we will go through his particular charges. The firſt is, that King James anno 1579 required the generall Aſſembly, to make no alteration in the Church-policy, till the next Parliament, but they contemning their Kings command, determined poſitively all their diſcipline without delay, and queſtioned the Arch-Biſhop of S. Andrews for voting in Parliament according to the undoubted Laws of the land, yea 20 Presbyters did hold the generall Aſſembly at Aberdeen after it was diſcharged by the King. <hi>Anſ.</hi> The VVar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner poſſibly may know, yet certainly he doth not care what he writes in theſe things to which he is a meer ſtranger: the authentick Regiſters of the Church of Scotland convinces him here of falſhood.<note place="margin">Biſhops were aboliſhed and Presb teries ſet up in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with King Iames conſent.</note> His Majeſty did write from Stirling to the Generall Aſſembly at Edenburg 1579. that they ſhould ceaſe from concluding any thing in the diſcipline of the Church, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of his minority; upon this deſire the Aſſembly did abſtaine from all concluſions, only they named a Committee to go to Striveling for conference with his Majeſtie upon that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. What followeth thereupon? I. Immediately a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is called in October 1579, and in the firſt Act declares and grants juriſdiction unto the Kirk, which conſiſts in the true
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110929:9"/> preaching of the word of Jeſus Chriſt, correction of manners, and adminiſtration of the true Sacraments, and declares that there is no other face of Kirk, nor other face of Religion then is preſently by the favour of God eſtabliſhed within this realm, and that there be no other juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical acknowledged within this Kingdom then that which is within the ſamen Kirk, or that which flowes therefrom concerning the premiſſes. II. In <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril</hi> 1580 Proclamation was made <hi>ex deliberatione Dominorum Conſilii</hi> in name of the King, charging all Superintendents and Commiſſioners and Miniſters ſerving at Kirks. To note the names of all the Subjects aſwel men as women ſuſpected to be Papiſts or—and to admonniſh them—to give Confeſſion of their faith acording to the form approved by the Parliament, and to ſubmit unto the diſcipline of the true Kirk within a reaſonable ſpace—: and if they fail—that the Superintendents or Commiſſioners preſent a role or catalogue of their names un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King and Lords of ſecret Counſel where they ſhall be for the time between and the 15 day of <hi>July</hi> next to come, to the end that the acts of Parliament made againſt ſuch perſons may be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute. III. The ſhort confeſſion was drawn up at the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which was firſt ſubſcribed by his royal hand, and an act of Secret Counſel commanding all ſubjects to ſubſcribe the ſame; as it is to be ſeen by the Act printed with the Confeſſion, wherein Hierarchie is abjured, that is (as hath been ſince declared by Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal aſſemblies and Parliaments both called and held by the King) Epiſcopacy is abjured. IV. In the aſſemblies 1580 and 1581, that Confeſſion of faith and the ſecond book of diſcipline (after debating many praeceding yeares) were approved (except one chapter <hi>de diaconatu</hi>) by the Aſſembly, the Kings Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners being alwayes preſent, nor finde we anything oppoſed them by him: yea then at his Majeſties ſpecial direction about fifty claſſical Presbyteries were ſet over Scotland which remain unto this day; was there here any attempt of the royal authority?</p>
            <p>About that time ſome noble men had got the revenues of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop-ricks for their private uſe; and becauſe they could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them by any legal right, therefore for eluding the Law, they did effectuate that ſome Miniſters ſhould have the title of this or that Biſhoprick; and the revenues were gathered in the name of this titulare or tulchan Biſhop, albeit he had but little part: e. g.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110929:10"/> 
               <hi>Robert Montgomery</hi> Miniſter at Sterline was called Arch-Biſhop of Glaſgow: and ſo it can be inſtanced in other Biſhop-ricks and Abbacies. Now this kind of praelats pretended no right to any part of the Epiſcopal office, either in ordination or juriſdiction: when ſome of theſe men began to creep in to vote for the Church in Parliament, without any Law of the State, without any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the Church, the General aſſembly diſcharged them, being Miniſters, to practiſe any more ſuch illegal inſolencies with this ordinance of the Church; after a little debate, King <hi>James</hi> at that time did ſhew his good ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the much maligned aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdeen.</note>But the Warner here jumps over no leſs then twenty ſeven years time from the aſſembly at Edingburgh 1579. to that at Aberdeen 1605. then was King <hi>James</hi> by the Engliſh Biſhops perſwaſion reſolved to put down the general aſſemblies of Scotland, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Lawes and conſtant practice of that Church, from the firſt reformation to that day. The act of Parliament did bear that once at leaſt a year the aſſembly ſhould meet, and after their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was ended they ſhould name time and place for the next aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly. When they had met in the yeer 1602, they were moved to adjurn without doing any thing for two whole years to 1604, when then they were conveened at the time and place agreed to by his Majeſtie, they were content upon his Majeſties deſire with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing any thing to adjourn to the next year 1605, at Aberdeen; when that dyet came, his Majeſties Commiſſioner offered him a Letter: To the end they might be an Aſſembly and ſo in a Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to receive his Majeſties Letter, with the Commiſſioners good pleaſure they ſate down, they named their Moderator and Clark, they received and read the Kings letter commanding them to riſe, which they obeyed without any further action at all but naming a dyet for the next meeting according to the conſtant practiſe of Scotland; hereupon by the pernicious counſel of the Arch-Biſhop <hi>Banckroft</hi> at London, the King was ſtirred up to bring ſore trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles upon a number of gratious Miniſters. This is the whole matter which to the Warner here is ſo tragick an inſolence, that never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Parliament durſt attempt the like. See more of this in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricall vindication.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Chriſtmas and other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivals aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Scotland, both by Church and State.</note>The next inſtance of our Presbiteryes uſurpation upon the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, is their abolition (before any ſtatute of Parliament there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon) of the Church feſtivals in their firſt book of diſcipline. Anſ.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110929:10"/> Conſider the griveouſneſs of this crime; in the intervall of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the great Councel of Scotland in the minority of the Prince entruſted by Parliament to rule the Kingdom, did charge the Church to give them in write their judgement about matters Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall: in obedience to this charge the Church did preſent the councel with a write named ſince the firſt book of diſcipline a which the Lords of councel did approve, ſubſcribe and ratifie by an Act of State: a part of the firſt head in that write was that Chriſtmas, Epiphany, Purification, and other fond feaſts of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> as not warrented by the holy Scriptures, ſhould be laid aſide. Was it any encroachment upon the Magiſtrate for the Church to give this advice to the privy councel when earneſtly they did crave it? the people of Scotland ever ſince have ſhewed their ready obedience to that direction of the Church founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Scripture, and backed from the beginning with an injunction of the State.</p>
            <p>His third inſtance of the Church of Scotlands uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the Magiſtrate, is,<note place="margin">The friends of Epiſcopacy thryves not in Scotland.</note> their abolition of Epiſcopacy in the aſſembly, 1580, when the Law made it treaſon to impugne the Authority of Biſhops, being the third eſtate of the Kingdom. Anſ. The Warner ſeems to have no more knowledge of the affaires of Scotland, then of Japan or Uto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia; the Law he ſpeaks of was not in being ſome years after 1580, however all the general aſſemblies of Scotland, are authoriſed by Act of Parliament, to determin finally without an appeal in all Ecleſiaſtick affairs: in the named aſſembly <hi>Lundie</hi> the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner did ſit and conſent in his Majeſties name to that act of abolition, as in the next aſſembly 1581, the Kings Commiſſioner <hi>Caprinton</hi> did erect in his Majeſties name the Presbyteries in all the Land; it is true, three years thereafter a wicked Courtier Captain <hi>James Stuart,</hi> in a ſhadow of a cloſe and not ſummoned Parliament, did procure an act to aboliſh Presbyterie and erect Biſhops; but for this and all other crimes that evil man was quickly rewarded by God before the world, in a terrible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: theſe acts of this Parliament the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t year were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed by the King, the Biſhops were put down and the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery was ſet up again, and never more removed to this day.</p>
            <p>The Warners digreſſion to the perpetuity of Biſhops in Scotland, to the acts of the Church and State for their reſtitution, is but to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110929:11"/> ſhew his ignorance in the Scots ſtory: what ever be the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall boaſting of other Nations, yet it is evident that from the firſt entrance of Chriſtian Religion into Scotland, Presbyters alone without Biſhops for ſome hundred years did govern the Church: and after the reformation there was no Biſhop in that Land, but in tittle and benefice till the year 1610; when Bancroft did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate three Scots Miniſters, all of them men of evil report; whom that violent Commiſſioner the Earl of <hi>Dunbar</hi> in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and nul aſſembly of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> got authoriſed in ſome part of a Biſhops office; which part only and no more was ratified in a poſterior Parliament. Superintendents are nowhere the ſame with Biſhops, much leſs in Scotland, where for a time only til the Churches were planted, they were uſed as ambulatory Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, and viſitors to preach the word, and adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments for the ſupply of vacant and unſetled congregations.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond book of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline why not at all ratified in Parliament.</note>The fourth inſtance is the Churches obtruding the ſecond book of diſcipline, without the ratification of the State. Anſ. For the Eccleſiaſtick enjoyning of a general aſſemblies decrees, a particular ratification of Parliament is unneceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry; general acts of Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment commanding obedience to the acts of the Church, are a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient warrant from the State; beſide, that ſecond book of diſciplin was much debated with the King, and at laſt in the General aſſembly 1590, his conſent was obtained unto it: for in that aſſembly where unanimouſly the ſubſcription of the ſecond book of diſciplin by all the miniſters of the Kingdom was decryed, his Majeſtie ſome time in perſon &amp; always by the Chancelor his Commiſſioner was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and in the act for ſubſcription. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 10 <hi>Auguſti</hi> 8. it is expreſly ſaid that not only all the Miniſters, but alſo all the Commiſſioners preſent did conſent, among which Commiſſioners the chancelor, his Majeſties Commiſſioner was chief. But neither the King nor the Church could get it to paſſe the Parliament in regard of the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which ſome States-men did make unto theſe parts thereof, which touched on their own intereſt of unjuſt advantage; this was the only ſtick.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Warners hypocriſy, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that a crime, which himſelf counts a vertue.</note>The next inſtance of the Churches encroachment is their uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of all the old rents of the clergy, as the Churches patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and their decerning in an aſſembly that nothing in the next Parliament ſhould paſſe before the Church were fully reſtored to her rents. Anſ. Conſider here the Warners hypocriſie and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110929:11"/> he challenges the Presbyterians for that which no Prelate in the world did ever eſteem a fault, a meer declaration of their judgment, that the Church had a juſt right to ſuch rents, as by Law and long poſſeſſion were theirs, and not taken away from them by any lawfull means. What if here they had gone on with the moſt of the prelatical party to advance that right to a <hi>jus divinum?</hi> what if they had put themſelves by a command from Court, into the poſſeſſion of that right, without a proceſſe, as divers of the Warners friends were begun lately to do in all the three Kingdoms? But all that he can here challenge the Scots for, is a meer declaration of their ſimple right, with a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the Regent his Grace, that he would indeavour in the next Parliament, to procure a ninth part of the Churches pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, for the maintenance of the miniſtry, and the poor of the Country: for all the rent that the Churches then could obtain, or did petition, was but a third of the Thirds of the Benefices or Tithes. That ever any Aſſembly in <hi>Scotland</hi> did make any other addreſſe to the Parliament for ſtipends, then by way of humble ſupplication, it is a great untruth.</p>
            <p>The laſt inſtance is, the erecting of Presbyteries through all the Kingdom, by an Act of the Church alone. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have ſhewn already the untruth of this Allegation; the proof here brought for it, is grounded only upon an ambiguous word, which the Warners ignorance in the Scotiſh Diſcipline and Presbytery (though the main ſubject of his Book) permits him not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. The Presbyteries were ſet up by the King after the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly 1580; but the ſecond Book of Diſcipline, of which alone the citation ſpeaks, how-ever injoyned by many Aſſemblies, yet it could never be gotten ratified in any parliament, only becauſe of thoſe parts of it which did ſpeak for the patrimony of the Church, and oppugne the right of patronage.</p>
            <p>How well the Warner hath proved the Presbyterian practices to be injurious to the Magiſtrate, we have conſidered;<note place="margin">The Warner a groſs Eraſtian.</note> poſſibly he will be more happy in his next undertaking, in his demonſtrations that their doctrinal principles do trample on the Magiſtrates Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy and Laws. Their firſt principle he takes out of the ſecond book of Diſcipline, Chap. 7. That no Magiſtrate, nor any but Eccleſiaſtick perſons may vote in Synods. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though I finde nothing of this in the place cited, yet there is nothing in it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110929:12"/> that croſſeth either the Laws, or the Kings Supremacy: for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Acts of Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> both old and late, and the conſtant practice of that Church, the onely members of Presbyteries are Miniſters and ruling Elders. Is it the Warners minde to vent here his ſuper-Eraſtianiſm, that all Eccleſiaſtick Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, Claſſical, Provincial, National, are but the arbitrary courts of the Magiſtrate, for to adviſe him in the execution of his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent power about matters Eccleſiaſtical; and for this cauſe, that it is in his arbitrement to give a deciſive voice in all Church Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles to whom and how many ſoever he will? Though this may be the Warners minde, as it hath been ſome of his friends; yet the moſt of the prelatical party will not maintain him herein. How-ever, ſuch principles are contrary to the Laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the profeſſions alſo and practices of all the Princes and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates that ever have lived there.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prelaticall principles im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilitate all ſolid peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the King and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</note>But the Warner here may poſſibly glance at another principle of his good friends, who have been willing lately to vent before all Brittain in print, their elevating the ſupremacy of Soveraigns ſo far above Laws, that whatever people have obtained to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by never ſo many Aſſemblies and Parliaments, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with never ſo many great ſeals of ratification, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably enjoyed by never ſo long a poſſeſſion; yet it is nothing but commendable wiſdom and juſtice for the ſame Prince who made the firſt Conceſſions, or any of his ſucceſſors, whenever they find themſelves ſtrong enough, to cancel all, and make void what ever Parliaments, Aſſemblies, Royall ratifications, and the longeſt poſſeſſion, made fooliſh people beleeve to be moſt firm and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable. To this purpoſe, Biſhop <hi>Maxwel</hi> (from whom much of this VVarning is borrowed) doth ſpeak in his <hi>Sacro-Sancta regum Majeſtas.</hi> Though this had bin the Cabin-divinity of our Prelats, yet what can be their intentions in ſpeaking of it out in theſe times of confuſion, themſelves muſt declare: for the clear conſequent of ſuch doctrine ſeems to be a neceſſity either of ſuch Warners perpetuall baniſhment from the Courts and ears of Soveraigns, or elſe that ſubjects be kept up for ever in a ſtrong jealouſie, and fear that they can never be ſecure of their Liberties, though never ſo well ratified by Lawes and promiſes of Princes any longer then the ſword and power remains in their own hand to preſerve what they have obtained. Such Warners,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110929:12"/> ſo long as they are poſſeſſed with ſuch maximes of ſtate, are clear everters of the firſt fundations of truſt betwixt Soveraigne and Subjects, they take away any poſſibility of any ſolid peace of any confident ſettlement in any troubled State, before both parties be totally ruined, or one become ſo ſtrong that they need no more to feare the others malecontentment in any time to come.</p>
            <p>Our ſecond challenged principle is that we teach the whole power of convocating aſſemblies to be in the Church.<note place="margin">Eraſtian Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats evert the legal foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</note> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Warners citations prove not that we maintain any ſuch aſſertion; our doctrin and conſtant practiſe hath been to aſcribe to the King a power of calling Synods, when and whereſoever he thought fit; but that which the Warner ſeems to point at is, our tenet of an intrinſicall power in the Church to meet, as for the Word and Sacraments, ſo for diſcipline; in this all who are Chriſtians, old and late, the Prelaticall and Popiſh party as well as others, go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with us to maintain in doctrin and practiſe a neceſſity e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in times of perſecution, that the Church muſt meet for the worſhip of God and execution of Eccleſiaſtick diſcipline among their own Members. In this the doctrine and practiſe of the Scots is according to their ſetled laws, uncontroverted by his Majeſtie. If the VVarner will maintain, that in reaſon and conſcience all the Churches of the world are obliged to diſſolve and never more to meet when an erroneous Magiſtrate by his Tyrannous E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict commands them to do ſo, let him call up Eraſtus from the dead to be diſciplined in this new doctrine of the Prelats impious loyalty.</p>
            <p>The third Principle is that the judgment of true and falſe doctrine,<note place="margin">The finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of all Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick cauſes by the Laws of Scotland, is in the generall Aſſembly.</note> of ſuſpenſion and deprivation of Miniſters belongeth to the Church. <hi>Anſ.</hi> If this be a great hereſie, it is to be charged as much upon the State as upon the Church, for the Acts of Parliament give all this power to the Church, neither did the Laws of England or of any Chriſtian State, Popiſh or Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, refuſe to the Church the determination of ſuch Ecccleſiaſtick cauſes; ſome indeed do debate upon the power of appeals from the Church; but in Scotland, by the Law, as no appeal in things civil goes higher then the Parliament, ſo in matters Eccleſiaſtick none goes above the Generall Aſſembly. Complaints indeed may go to the King and Parliament for redreſſe of any wrong has been done in Eccleſiaſtick Courts, who being <hi>Cuſtodes Religionis</hi> may by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110929:13"/> their coercive power command Eccleſiaſtick Courts to rectifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wrong done by them contary to Scripture, or if they perſiſt take order with them. But that two or three P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aelates ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Court of delegates, to receive appeals from a general aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, neither Law nor practice in Scotland did ever admit, nor doth the word of God or any Equity require it. In the Scots aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies no cauſes are agitat but ſuch as the Parliament hath agreed to be Eccleſiaſtick and of the Churches cogniſance: no proceſs about any Church rent was ever cognoſced upon in Scotland but in a civill Court: its very falſe that ever any Church cenſure, much leſſe the higheſt of excommunication did fall upon any for robbing the Church of its patrimony.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The divine right of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, is the tenet of the moſt of Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats.</note>Our fourth challenged principle is that we maintain Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick juriſdiction by a divine right. Anſ. Is this a huge crime? is there divine right in the world, either Papiſt or Proteſtant, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a few praelatical Eraſtians, but they doe ſo? If the Warner will profeſs (as it ſeems he muſt) the contradiction of that which he aſcribes to us, his avowed tenet muſt be that all Eccleſiaſtick power flowes from the Magiſtrate, that the Magiſtrate himſelf may execute all Church cenſures, that all the Officers appointed by Chriſt for the government of his Church, may be laid aſide, and ſuch a kind of governors be put in their place, as the Magiſtrate ſhall be pleaſed to appoint: that the ſpiritual ſword and Keyes of heaven belong to the Magiſtrate by vertue of his ſupremacy, as wel as the temporal ſword and Keyes of his earthly Kingdom: our difference herefrom the Warner will not (I hope) be found the greateſt hereſie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All the power of the Church in Scotland is legal, and with the Magiſtrates conſent.</note>Our laſt challenged principle is, that we will have all our power againſt the Magiſtrate, that is, although he diſſent. Anſ. It is an evil commentary that all muſt be againſt the Magiſtrate, which is done againſt his conſent: but in Scotland there is no ſuch caſe: for all juriſdiction which the Church there doth enjoy, they have it with the conſent of the Magiſtrate: all is ratified to them by ſuch acts of Parliament as his Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtie doth not at all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trovert. Concerning that odious caſe the Warner intimates, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in time of perſecution, when the Magiſtrate claſsheth with the Church, any Eccleſiaſtick diſcipline be then to be exerciſed; himſelf can better anſwer it then we, who with the ancient Chriſtians do think that on all hazards (even of life) the Church
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110929:13"/> may not be diſſolved, but meet in dens and in the caves and in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs for the word and Sacraments and keeping it ſelf pure by the divine ordinance of Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Having cleered all the pernicious practiſes and all the wicked D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctrines, which the Warner layes upon us,<note place="margin">The Prelats rather then to lay aſide their own intereſt, will keep the King and his people in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery for ever.</note> I think it needleſs to inſiſt upon theſe defences which he in his abundant charity brings for us; but in his own way, that he may with the greater advantage impugne them: only I touch one paſſage whereupon he makes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious exclamations: that which Mr. <hi>Gileſpie</hi> in his theoremes writes; when the Magiſtrate abuſes his power unto Tyranny and makes havock of all, it is lawful to reſiſt him by ſome extraordinary wayes and means, which are not ordinarily to be allowed: ſee the principles from which all our miſeries and the loſs of our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Maſter hath flowed. Anſ. We muſt here yeeld to the Warner the great equity and neceſſity that every doctrine of a Presbyter, ſhould be charged on the Presbytery it ſelf, and that any Presbyter teaching the lawfulneſs of a Parliaments defenſive arms is tantamont to the Churches taking of armes againſt the King. Theſe ſmal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſequences we muſt permit the Warner to ſwallow down with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſtick; however we do deny that the maxime in hand was the fountain of any of our miſeries, or the cauſe at all of the loſs of our late Soveraign: Did ever his Majeſty or any of his adviſed Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors declare it ſimply unlawful for a Parliament, to take arms for defence in ſome extraordinary caſes, however the unhappineſs of the Canterburian Praelats did put his Majeſty upon theſe courſes, which did begin and promote all our miſerie; and to the very laſt theſe men were ſo wicked as to refuſe the looſing of the bands which their hands had tyed about his miſinformed conſcience, yea to this day they will not give their conſent, that his Majeſtie, who now is, ſhould lay aſide Epiſcopacy, were it for the gaining of the peaceable poſſeſſion of all his three Kingdoms, but are urgers of him night and day to adhere to their errours, upon the hazard of all the miſeries that may come on his perſon, on his family, and all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; yet few of them to this day durſt be ſo bold as to print with this Warner, the unlawfulneſs of a Parliaments armes againſt the Tyranny of a Prince in any imaginable caſe, how extraordinary ſoever.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Lawes and cuſtomes of Scotland admit of no appeal from the general aſſembly.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN this Chapter the challenge is, that there are no appeals from the general Aſſembly to the King, as in England from the Biſhops
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110929:14"/> Courts to the King in Chauncery,<note place="margin">Appeales in Scotland from a generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly were no leſſe irrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal then ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall.</note> where a Commiſſion uſes to be given to delegats who diſcuſſe the appeals. Anſ. The warner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders not the difference of the Government of the Church of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, from that which was in England; what the Parliament is in the State, that the general aſſembly is in the Church of Scotland: both are the higheſt Courts in their own kinde. There is no appeal any where in moderate Monarchies to the Kings perſon, but to the King in certain legall Courts, as the Warner here confeſſeth the appeal from Biſhops lies not to the King in his perſon, but to the King in his Court of Chancery. As no man in Scotland is permitted to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal in a civill cauſe from the Lords of Seſſion, much leſſe from the Parliament; ſo no man in an eccleſiaſtick cauſe is permitted by the very civil Law of Scotland, to appeal from the general Aſſembly. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scots order and practice, the King in perſon, or elſe by his high Commiſſioner, ſits as uſually in the generall Aſſembly, as in Parliament. But though it were not ſo, yet an appeal from a generall Aſſembly, to be diſcuſſed in a court of Delegats, were unbeſeeming and unreaſonable; the one court conſiſting of above two hundred, all cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen men, the beſt and moſt able of the Kingdom; the other but of two or three, often of very ſmall either abilities or integrity, who yet may be more fit to diſcern in an Eccleſiaſtick cauſe, then a ſingle Biſhop or his Official, the ordinary Truſtee in all acts of Jurisdiction for the whole Dioces. But the Scots way of managing Eccleſiaſtick cauſes is a great deal more juſt, ſafe and Satisfactory to any rational man, then that old Popiſh order of the Engliſh, where all the ſpirituall Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the whole Dioces was in the hand of one mercenary Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, without all relief from his Sentence, except by an appeal, as of old to the Pope and his Delegats, ſo thereafter to the King, though never to be cognoſced upon by himſelf; but as it was of old by two or three Delegats, the weakeſt of all Courts, often for the quality, and ever for the number of the Judges.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Churches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ſeverity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inſt Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mery &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mſon was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>proven by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e King and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e parties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mſelves.</note>Two Inſtances are brought by the Warner, to prove the Church of Scotlands ſtopping of appeals from the generall Aſſembly to the King, the caſes of <hi>Montgomery</hi> and <hi>Adamſon:</hi> if the cauſes and events of the named caſes had been well known to the Warner, as he made this chapter diſproportionably ſhort, ſo readily be might have deleted it altogether. But theſe men were infamous not onely in their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall charges, but in their life and converſation; both became ſo inſolent, that contrary to the eſtabliſhed order of the Church and Kingdom, being ſuborned by wicked Stateſmen, who in that day of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110929:14"/> darkneſs had well neer brought ruine both to King and Countrey, would needs take upon them the Office of Arch-Biſhops. While the Aſſembly was in Proceſs with them for their manifold and high miſdeameanors, the King was moved by them and their evil Patrons, to ſhew his high diſpleaſure againſt the Aſſemblies of the Church; they for his Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſties ſatisfaction ſent their Commiſſioners and had many conferences; whereby the pride and contempt of theſe Prelats did ſo encreaſe, that at laſt they drew the ſentence of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication upon their own heads: the King after ſome time did acknowledge the equity of the Church proceedings, and profeſſed his contentment therewith: both theſe unhappy men were brought to a humble confeſſion of their crimes, and ſuch ſigns of repentance, that both after a renunciation of their titulary Biſhopricks were re-admitted to the function of the Miniſtry, which they had deſerted. Never any other before or after in <hi>Scotland</hi> did appeal from the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly to the King; the late Excommunicate Prelate in their declinator againſt the Aſſembly of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> did not appeal as (I remember) to the King, but to another Generall Aſſembly to be conſtitute, according to their own Popiſh and Tyrannicall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Faulty Miniſters in <hi>Scotland</hi> are leſſe exempted from puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then any other men.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe Warner in his fourth Chapter,<note place="margin">The pride of Prelats lately, but never the Presbytery did exempt their fellows from puniſhment for their civill faults.</note> offers to prove that the Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Diſcipline doth exempt Miniſters from puniſhment for any treaſon or ſedition they can act in their Pulpits. <hi>Anſw.</hi> This chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge is like the reſt, very falſe. The rules of the Church Diſcipline in <hi>Scotland</hi> obliges Churchmen to be ſubject to puniſhment, not only for every fault for which any other man is lyable to cenſure, but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains them to be puniſhed for ſundry things, which in other men are not at all queſtionable; and whatever is conſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able in any, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point it to be much more ſo in a Miniſter. It is very untru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that the Pulpits in <hi>Scotland</hi> are Sanctuaries for any crime, much leſſe for the grievous crimes of ſedition and treaſon. Let the Warner remember, how ſhort a time it is, ſince an Epiſcopall Chaire or a Canonicall Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t did priviledge in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> from all cenſure either of Church or State great numbers, who were notoriouſly known to be guilty of the fouleſt crimes. Was ever the War<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> companion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110929:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:110929:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:110929:16"/> Biſhop <hi>Aderton</hi> challenged for his Sodomy, ſo long as their common Patron of <hi>Canterbury</hi> did rule the Court? did the Warner never hear of a Prelate very ſibb to D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctor <hi>Bramble,</hi> who to this day was never called to any account for flagrant ſcandals of ſuch crimes as in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are puniſhable by the Gallows? the Warner doth not well to inſiſt upon the <hi>Scots</hi> Clergy, exempting themſelves from civill pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments; no where in the world are Churchmen more free of crimes deſerving civill Cogniſance then in <hi>Scotland:</hi> and if the ears and eyes of the World may be truſted, the Popiſh Clergy this day in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> are not ſo challengeable, as the Prela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icall Divines in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> lately were for many groſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miſdemeanors.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Warner is injurious to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note>But why does the Warners anger run out ſo far as to the Preachers in <hi>Holland?</hi> is it becauſe he knoweth the Church D ſcipline in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be really the ſame with that he oppugnes in the <hi>Scots,</hi> and that all the Reformed Churches doe joyn cordially with <hi>Scotland</hi> in their rejection of Epiſcopacy? is this a ground for him to ſlander our Brethren of <hi>Holland?</hi> Is it charity for him a ſtranger to publiſh to the World in print, that the Miniſters in <hi>Holland</hi> are ſeditious Orators, and that they ſaucily controll the Magiſtrates in their Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits? Their crime ſeems to be, that for the love of Chriſt their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, they are zealous in their doctrine, to preſſe upon the Magiſtrate as well as upon the people the true practice of piety, the ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sabbath day, the ſuppreſſion of hereſy and ſchiſm, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for the ſins of the time and place wherein they live. I his is a crime, whereof few of the Warners friends were wont to be guilty of: their ſhamefull ſilence and flattery was one of the great cauſes of all the ſins and calamities that have wracked the three Kingdoms: the ſtream of their Sermons while they enjoyed the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, was to encourage to ſuperſtition and contempt of piety, to ſing aſleep by their ungracious way all that gave ear unto them. The man is impatient to ſee the Paſtors of <hi>Holland</hi> or any where, to walk in another path then his own, and for this cauſe would ſtirre up their Magiſtrates againſt them: as it was his and his Brethrens cuſtom to ſtir up the Magiſtrates of <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> to impriſon, baniſh, and heavily vex the moſt zealous ſervants of God, only for their oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Prelats profanity and errours. The Warner (I hope) has not yet forgotten, how Doctor <hi>Bramble</hi> and his neighbour <hi>Leſty</hi> of Down did caſt out of the Miniſtry, and made flee our of the Kingdom, men moſt eminent for zeal, piety and learning, who in a ſhort time had done more good in the houſe of God, then all the Biſhops that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110929:16"/> ever were in Ireland, I mean Mr. <hi>Blair,</hi> Mr. <hi>Levington,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cuningham,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>The Warner needed not to have marked as a ſingularity of Geneva, that there all the Eccleſiaſticks, <hi>quâ tales,</hi> are puniſhable by the Magiſtrats for civil crimes; for we know none of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, who were ever following Rome in exempting the Clergy from ſaecular juriſdiction, except it were the Canterburian Praelates: who indeed did ſcare the moſt of Magiſtrats from medling with a canonical coat though defiled with drunkenneſs, adultery, ſcolding, fighting, and other evils, which were too common of late to that order.</p>
            <p>But how doth he prove,<note place="margin">The pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed declaration of King <hi>James,</hi> was Biſhop A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damſons lying libel.</note> that the Scots Miniſters exempt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from civil juriſdiction? firſt (ſaith he) by the declaration of King <hi>James</hi> 1584. Anſ. That declaration was not from King <hi>James,</hi> as himſelf did teſtifie the year thereafter under his hand, but from Mr. <hi>Patrike Adamſon,</hi> who did acknowledge it to be his own upon his death bed, and profeſſed his repentance for the lyes and ſlanders, wherewith againſt his conſcience he had fraughted that infamous libell.</p>
            <p>His ſecond proof is from the ſecond book of diſciplin Chapter II,<note place="margin">Though al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land yet never in Scotland had Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries any ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction over Miniſters.</note> It is abſurd that Commiſſaries having no function in the Church, ſhould be judges to Miniſters to depoſe them from their charges. Anſ. Though in England the Commiſſary and officiall was the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary judge to depoſe and excommunicate all the Miniſters of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſe, yet by the Laws of Scotland no Commiſſaries had ever any ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction over Miniſters. But though the officials juriſdiction toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their Lords the Biſhops were aboliſhed, yet doth it follow from this, that no other juriſdiction remaineth whereby Miniſters might be puniſhed either by Church or State, according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits? is not this ſtrongly reaſoned by the Warner?</p>
            <p>His third proofe is the cauſe of <hi>James Gibſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>James Gibſon</hi> was never ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by the Church from his Proceſs.</note> who had railed in Pulpit againſt the King, and was only ſuſpended; yea, thereaft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r was abſolved from that fault. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Upon the complaint of the Chancelor the alledged words were condemned by the generall Aſſembly: but before the mans guiltineſs of theſe words could be tryed, hee did abſent himſelfe; for which abſence, he was preſently ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from his Miniſtry: in the next Aſſembly he did appeare and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the reaſon of his abſence to have been juſt feare, and no contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy; this he made appeare to the Aſſemblies ſatisfaction, but before his proceſſe could bee brought to any iſſue, he fled away to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110929:17"/> England, where he died a fugitive, never reſtored to his charge though no tryal of his fault was perfected.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mr. Blacks ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Councel cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note>The fourth proof is Mr. Black his caſe: hereupon the Warner makes a long and odious narration. If we interrogate him about his ground of all theſe Stories, he can produce no warrant but <hi>Spotſwoods</hi> unprinted Book: this is no an h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tick R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>giſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r whereupon any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding man can rely; the Writer was a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ofeſt enemy, to his death, of the Scotiſh Diſcipline, he ſpent his life upon a Story for the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſgrace of the Presbytery and the honour of Biſhops: no man who is acquainted with the life or death of that Authour, will build his belief upon his words. This whole narration is abundantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed in the hiſtoricall Vindication, when the Warner is pleaſed to repeat the Challenge from Iſſachars burden, he ought to have replyed ſomething after three yeers adviſement to the printed Anſwer.</p>
            <p>The matter (as our Regiſters bear) was ſhortly thus: In the yeer 1596. the Popiſh and Malignant Faction in King JAMES his Court grew ſo ſtrong, that the countenance of the King towards the Church was much changed, and over all the Land great fears did daily encreaſe, of the overthrow of the Church Diſcipline eſtabliſhed by Law. The Miniſters in their Pulpits gave free warning thereof: among others, Mr. <hi>Black</hi> of S. Andrews, a moſt gracious and faithfull paſtor, did apply his doctrine to the ſins of the time; ſome of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies delated him at Court for words injurious to the King and Queen: the words he did deny and all his honeſt hearers did abſolve him by their teſtimony from theſe calumnies: of himſelf he was moſt willing to be tryed to the uttermoſt before all the world, but his Brethren finding the libelled calumnies to be onely a pretence, and the true intention of the Courtiers therein was to ſtop the mouthes of Miniſters, that the crying ſins of the times ſhould no more be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in pulpits, they adviſed him to decline the judgment of the councell, and appeal to the general Aſſembly, as the competent Judge according to the word of God and the Laws of Scotland, in the cauſe of doctrine; for the firſt inſtance they did never queſtion, but if any thing truely ſeditious had been preached by a Miniſter, that he for this might be called before the civil Magiſtrate, and accordingly puniſhed; but that every Miniſter for the application of his doctrine according to the rules of Scripture to the ſins of his hearers for their reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, ſhould be brought before a civil court at the firſt inſtance, they thought it unreaſonable, and deſired the King in the next Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly might cognoſce upon the equity of ſuch a proceeding. The
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110929:17"/> Miniſters had many a conference with his Majeſty upon that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct; often the mat er was brought very near to an amicable conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but becauſe the Miniſters refuſed to ſubſcibe a band for ſo great a ſilence as the Court required againſt his Majeſties countenancing of treacherous Papiſts, and favouring the enemies of Religion, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Sentence was pronounced not only againſt Maſter <hi>Black,</hi> but alſo all the Miniſters of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time,<note place="margin">The Tumult of the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of December was harmleſs, and no Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter guilty of it.</note> malcontented States-men did adde oyl to the flame, and at the very inſtant, while the Miniſters and their friends are offering a Petition to his Majeſty, they ſuborn a villane to cry in one part of the Streets, That the Miniſters are ſlain, and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of the Streets, That the King was killed: whereupon the People ruſh all out to the Streets in their Armes, and for half an hour at moſt, were in a tumult, upon meer ignorance what the fray might be, but without the hurt of any one man; ſo ſoon as it was found that both the King and Miniſters were ſafe, the people went all peaceably to their houſes. This is the very truth of that innocent commotion, whereupon the Warner here and his fellowes elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where make all their Tragedies. None of the Miniſtry were the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors or approvers thereof, though divers of them ſuffered ſore troubles for it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>No Presbyterian ever intended to Excommunicate any Supream Magiſtrate.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe Warner in his fifth Chapter,<note place="margin">The Prelats ordinarily, but the Presbytery never were for raſh Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications.</note> charges the <hi>Scots</hi> for ſubjecting the King to the cenſure of Excommunication, and bringing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Princes all the miſeries which the Popes Excommunications of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d were wont to bring upon Anathematiſed Emperours. <hi>Anſ.</hi> It does not become the Warner and his fellowes to object to any, the abuſe of the dreadfull ſentence of Excommunication; no Church in the world was ever more guilty of that fault then the Prelats of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> did they ever cenſure their own Officials for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of that terrible ſentence moſt profanly againſt any they would, had it been for the non-payment of the ſmalleſt ſums of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney? As for the <hi>Scots,</hi> their doctrine and practice in the point of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication is as conſiderate as any other Church in the world, that cenſure in <hi>Scotland</hi> is moſt rare and only in the caſe of obſtinacy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110929:18"/> in a great ſin; what ever be their doctrine in generall with all other Chriſtians and as I think with the P elaticall party themſelves, that the object of Chriſtian doctrine Sacraments and Diſcipline is one and the ſame, and that no member of Chriſt, no ſon of the Church, may plead a highneſs above admonitions and Church Cenſures: yet I know they never thought it expedient ſo much as to intend any Proceſſe of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>dverſion againſt their Soveraign. To the worlds end I hope they ſhall not have again greater grievances and truer cauſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ritation from their Princes, th n they have had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. It may be confidently believed, that they who upon ſo preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant occaſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d never ſo much as intend the beginning of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs againſt their King, can never be ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſed in danger of any ſuch proceeding for time to come.<note place="margin">The Prelates flatter Princes to their ruine.</note> However, we love not the abuſed ground of the Warners flattering of Princes to their own great hur; is it ſo indeed, that all the ſins of the Princes are only againſt God, that all Kings are not only above all Laws of Church and State, but when they fall into the greateſt crimes, that the worſt of men have ever committed, that even then their ſins muſt not be againſt any man or againſt any Law? ſuch Epiſcopall Doctrine ſpurs on Princes to theſe unhappy precipices, and oppreſſed people unto theſe out-rages that both fall into inextricable calamities.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>It grieves the Prelates that Presbyterians are faithfull Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to admoniſh Princes of their duty.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Scots Miniſters Preaching for Juſtice, was juſt and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</note>THE ſixth Chapter is ſpent on an other crime of <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery;</hi> it makes the <hi>Presbyters</hi> cry to the Magiſtrate for Juſtice upon capitall Offenders. <hi>Anſ.</hi> What has <hi>Presbytery</hi> to doe with this matter, were it never ſo great an offence? will the Warner have all the faults of the Prelaticall Faction, flow from the fountain of Epiſcopacy? this unconſequentiall reaſoning will not be permitted to men below the degrees of Doctors. But was it a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great crime indeed for Miniſters to plead the cauſe of the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and widowes; yea, the cauſe of God their Maker and to preach unto Magiſtrates, that according to Scriptures murtherers, ought to die, and the Land bee purged from the ſtaine of innocent blood? when the ſhamefull impunity of murther made <hi>Scotland</hi> by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110929:18"/> deadly feuds, in time of peace a field of war and blood, was it not time for the faithful ſervants of God to exhort the King to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute juſtice, and to declare the danger of moſt frequent pardons drawn from his hand, often againſt his heart, by the opportunity and deceitfull information of powerful ſolicitors, to the great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of God againſt the whole Land, to the unexpreſſible grief and wrong of the ſuffering party, to the opening alſo of a new floodgate of more blood, which by a legall revenge in time eaſily might have been ſtopped? Too much pity in ſparing the wilfull ſhedders of innocent blood ordinarily proves a great cruelty, not only towards the diſconſolate oppreſſed, who cry to the vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of God the avenger, for juſtice in vain, but alſo towards the ſoul of him who is ſpared, and the life of many more who are friends either to the oppreſſor, or oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>As for the named caſe of <hi>Huntly</hi> let the world judge,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Huntleys</hi> notorious crymes.</note> whether the Miniſters had reaſon often to give Warning againſt that wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man and his complices. Beſide, his apoſtaſie, and after-ſeeming repentance, his frequent relapſes into avowed Popery, in Eighty eight he banded with the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to overthrow the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and government of the whole Iſland, and after pardon, from time to time did renew his treaſonable plots for the ruine of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain:</hi> he did commit many murders, he did invade under the noſe of the King, the houſe of his Couſin the Earl of <hi>Murray,</hi> and moſt cruelly murdered that gallant Nobleman, he appeared with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played Banner againſt the King in perſon, he killed thereafter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundreds of the Kings good people, when theſe multiplyed outrages did cry up to the God of heaven, was it not time for the men of God to cry to the Judges of the earth to doe their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, according to the warrant of many Scriptures? What a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous humor of flattery is this in our Prelates, not onely to lull a ſleep a Prince in a moſt ſinful neglect of his charge, but alſo to cry out upon others more faithful then themſelves, for aſſaying to break off their ſlumber,<note place="margin">Never any queſtion in <hi>Scotland</hi> betwixt the King &amp; the Church, for Tythes and Patronages.</note> by their wholſom and ſeaſonable admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions from the Word of God?</p>
            <p>The next challenge of the <hi>Scots</hi> Presbyters is, that they ſpoile the King of his Tythes, firſt Fruits, Patronage, and Dependence of his Subjects. <hi>Anſ.</hi> The <hi>Warner</hi> underſtands not what he writes, The Kings Majeſty in <hi>Scotland,</hi> never had, never craved any Firſt fruits: The Church never ſpoiled the King of any Tithes, ſome
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110929:19"/> other men indeed, by the wickedneſs moſt of Prelates and their followers, did cozen both the King, and the Church, of many Tythes: but his Majeſty and the Church had never any controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in <hi>Scotland</hi> about the Tythes: for the King, ſo far as concerned himſef, was ever willing, that the Church ſhould enjoy that, which the very Act of Parliament acknowledgeth to be her patrimony. Nor for the patronages had the Church any plea with the King: the Church declared often their mind of the iniquity of patrona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wherein they never had from the King any conſiderable oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, but from the Nobility and Gentry, the oppoſition was ſo great, that for peace ſake, the Church was content to let patrona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges alone, till God ſhould make a Parliament lay to heart, what was incumbent for gracious men to do, for liberating Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from their ſlavery of having Miniſters intruded upon them, by the violence of Patrons. Which now at laſt (bleſſed be God) according to our mind is performed. As for the dependence of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vaſſalls upon the King, it was never queſtioned by any Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian in <hi>S otla d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">K. <hi>James</hi> avowes himſelf a hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſm.</hi>
               </note>What is added in the reſt of the Chapter, is but a repetition of that which went before, to wit, the Presbyters denying to the King, the ſpirituall Government of the Church, and the power of the keys of the Kingdom of Heaven: ſuch an uſurpation upon the Church, King <hi>James</hi> declared under his hand (as at length may be ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in the Hiſtoricall vindication) to be a ſin againſt the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, which puts in the hand of the Magiſtrate the power of Preaching, and celebrating the Sacraments: a power which ſince that time no Magiſtrate in <hi>Britaine</hi> did aſſume, and if any would have claimed it, none would have more oppoſed, then the moſt zealous Patrons of Epiſcopacy. The injurious invectives which the <hi>Warner</hi> builds upon this his <hi>Eraſtian</hi> aſſertion, we paſs them as Caſtles in their ayr, which muſt fall and evaniſh for want of a foundation. Only before I leave this Chapter, let the <hi>Warner</hi> take a good Sentence out of the mouth of that wiſe Prince King <hi>James,</hi> to teſtifie yet farther his mind againſt <hi>Eraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme.</hi> His Majeſtie in the year 1617 having come in progreſs to viſit his ancient Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and being preſent in perſon at a publick diſputation in Theologie in the Univerſity of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> whereof alſo many, both Nobles, and Church-men of both Kingdoms were auditors; when one of thoſe that acted a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110929:19"/> part in the diſputation, had affirmed, and went about to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this Aſſertion, that the King had power to depoſe Miniſters from their Miniſteriall function. The King himſelf, as abhorring ſuch flattery, cried out with a loud voice, <hi>Ego poſſum deponere Miniſtri caput, ſed non poſſum deponere ejus officium.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Preſbytery doth not draw from the Magiſtrate any part of his power, by the cheat of any relation.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN the ſeventh Chapter,<note place="margin">The Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſceth only upon ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, and that in few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er civill things then Biſhops courts were wont to meddle with.</note> the <hi>Warner</hi> would cauſe men believe many more of the Presbyteries uſurpations upon the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. The firſt is, that all offences whatſoever, are cognoſcible in the Conſiſtory upon the caſe of ſcandal. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery makes no offence at all to come before the Conſiſtory, but Scandall alone. Secondly, theſe civil offences (the ſcandall where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of comes before the Presbytery) are but very few, and a great deal fewer then the Biſhops Official takes notice of in his Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorial Court. That capitall crimes paſt over by the Magiſtrate, ſhould be cenſured by the Church, no ſociety of Chriſtians who have any diſcipline, did ever call in queſtion. When the ſword of the Magiſtrate hath ſpared a Murderer, an Adulterer, a Blaſphemer; will any ingenuous, either Prelaticall, or Popiſh Divine, admit of ſuch to the holy Table, without ſigns of Repentance?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Warners</hi> ſecond uſurpation is but a branch of the firſt, that the Presbytery draws directly before it ſelf the cogniſance of fraud in bargaining, falſe meaſures, oppreſſion, and in the caſe of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, bribing, uſury, fighting, perjury, &amp;c. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is it then the <hi>Warners</hi> mind, that the notorious ſlander of ſuch groſſe ſins does not deſerve ſo much, as an Eccleſiaſticall rebuke? Shall ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons without admonition be admitted to the holy Communion? Secondly, the named caſes of fraud in bargaining, falſe meaſures, oppreſſion, come ſo rarely before our Church-judicatories, that though this thirty years I have been much converſant in Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yet did I never ſee, nor doe I remember that ever I heard any of theſe three caſes brought before any Church Aſſembly. In the perſon of Miniſters, I grant, theſe faults, which the Canons of the Church, in all times and places, make the cauſes of deprivation, are cognoſced upon in Presbyteries, but with the good liking (I am
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110929:20"/> ſure) of all both Papiſts and Prelates, who themſelves are free of ſuch vices. And why did not the <hi>Warner</hi> put in among the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Church-mens deprivation from Office and Benefice, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, gluttony, and Drunkenneſs? Are theſe in his, &amp;c. which he will not have cognoſcible by the Church in the perſons of Biſhops and Doctors?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Warners</hi> third challenge amounts to an high crime, that Presbyterian Miniſters are bold to preach upon theſe Scriptures which ſpeak of the Magiſtrates duty in his Office, or dare offer to reſolve from Scripture any doubt, which perplexeth the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Magiſtrates or People, of Husband or Wife, of Maſter or Servant, in the diſcharge of their Chriſtian duty one to another. What ever hath bin the negligence of the Biſhop of <hi>Derry,</hi> yet I am ſure, all the preaching Prelates and Doctors of <hi>England,</hi> pretended a great care to goe about theſe uncontroverted parts of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall Function, and yet without medling with the Myſteries of State, or the depths of any mans particular vocation; much leſs with the judgment of juriſdiction in Political or Aeconomical cauſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e late engage<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from miſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes.</note>As for the Churches declaration againſt the Late engagement; did it not well become them to ſignifie their judgment in ſo great a caſe of conſcience, eſpecially when the Parliament did propone it to them for reſolution, and when they found a conjunction driven on with a clearly Malignant Party, contrary to ſolemn oathes and covenants, unto the evident hazard of Religion, and them who had been moſt eminent inſtruments of its preſervation; was it not the Churches duty to give warning againſt that ſin, and to exhort the ring-leaders therein to repentance?</p>
            <p>But our <hi>Warner</hi> muſt needs inſiſt upon that unhappy engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and faſten great blame upon the Church for giving any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice about it. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Muſt it be Jeſuitiſme, and a drawing of all the civill affaires to the Churches bar <hi>in ordine ad Spiritualia,</hi> for an Aſſembly to give their advice in a moſt eminent and important caſe of conſcience, when earneſtly called upon in a multitude of ſupplications from the moſt of the Congregations under their charge; yea when required by the States of the Kingdom in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall expreſs meſſages for that end? It ſeems, its our <hi>Warners</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, if the Magiſtrate would draw all the Churches in his juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to a moſt unlawful war, for the advancement of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110929:20"/> impiety and unjuſtice poſſible, wherein nothing could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by all who were engaged therein, but the curſe of God; if in this caſe a doubting Souldier ſhould deſire the Aſſemblies coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell for the ſtate of his ſoul, or if the Magiſtrate would put the Church to declare what were lawfull or unlawfull according to the Word of God, that it were neceſſary here for the ſervants of God to be altogether ſilent, becauſe indeed war is ſo civill a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that nothing in it concerns the ſoul, and nothing about it may be cleared by any light from the Word of God.</p>
            <p>The truth is, the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rch in their publick papers to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, declared oftner then once, that they were not againſt, but for an engagement, if ſo that Chriſtian and friendly treaties could not have obtained reaſon, and all the good people in <hi>Scotland</hi> were willing enough to have hazarded their lives and eſtates, for vindicating the wrongs do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, not by the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> but by the Sectarian Party there, againſt God, the King, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and both Kingdoms: but to the great grief of their hearts, their hands were bound, and they forced to ſit ſtill, and by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver great cunning of ſome, the erronious miſ-perſwaſions of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the raſh precipitancy of it, that engagement was ſo ſpoyled in the ſtating and mannaging, that the moſt religious, with peace of conſcience could not go along, nor encourage any other to take part therein. The <hi>Warner</hi> touches on three of their reaſons: but who will look upon their publick declarations, ſhall find ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, which with all faithfulneſs were then propounded by the Church, for the rectifying of that action, which as it ſtood in the ſtate and management, was cleerly foretold to be exceeding like to deſtroy the King, and his friends of all ſorts, in all the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. The irrepairable loſſes and unutterable calamities which quickly did follow at the heels, the miſ-belief and contempt of the Lords ſervants, and the great danger Religion is now brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in all theſe Kingdoms, hath, I ſuppoſe, long agoe brought grief enough to the heart of them, whoſe unadviſed raſhneſs, &amp; intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate fervor did contribute moſt for the ſpoiling of that deſigne.</p>
            <p>The firſt deſire about that engagement which the <hi>Warner</hi> gives to us, concerns the ſecurity of Religion. In all the debate of that matter, it was agreed (without queſtion) upon all hands, that the Sectarian Party deſerved puniſhment for their wicked attempts upon the Kings perſon, contrary to the directions of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110929:21"/> of both Kingdoms, and that the King ought to be reſcued out of their hands, and brought to one of his Houſes for perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Treaty of Peace, which often had been begun: but here was the queſtion; Whether the Parliament and Army of <hi>Scotland</hi> ought to declare their reſolutions to bring his Majeſty to <hi>London</hi> with honor, freedome, and ſafety, before he did promiſe any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for eſtabliſhing Religion; The Parliaments of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms in all their former Treaties, had ever preſſed upon the King a number of Propoſitions to be ſigned by his Majeſty, before at all he came to <hi>London:</hi> was it then any fault in the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to deſire the granting but of one of theſe propoſitions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion &amp; the Covenant, before the King were brought (by the new hazard of the lives and eſtates of all the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to ſit in his Parliament in that honor and freedom which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did deſire? There was no complaint, when many of thirty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions were preſſed, to be ſigned by his Majeſty, for ſatisfaction and ſecurity to his people, after ſo great and long deſolations: how then is an out-cry made, when all other propoſitions are poſtpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and only one for Religion is ſtuck upon, and that not before his Majeſties reſcue and deliverance from the hands of the Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but only before his bringing to <hi>London,</hi> in honor, freedom, and ſafety? This demand, to the <hi>Warner</hi> is a crime, and may be ſo to all of his belief, who takes it for a high unjuſtice, to reſtraine in any King the abſolute power by any condition: for they do main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the adminiſtration of al things, both of Church and State, doth reſide ſo freely and abſolutely in the meer wil of a Soveraign, that no caſe at any time can fall out, which ought to bound that abſoluteneſs with any limitation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond particular the <hi>Warner</hi> pitches upon, is the Kings ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative voyce; behold how criminous we were in the point; When ſome (moſt needleſly) would needs bring into debate the Kings negative voice in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> as one of the royall Prerogatives to be maintained by our engagement: it was ſaid, that all diſcourſe of that kind might be laid aſide, as impertinent for us: if any debate ſhould chance to fall upon it, the proper place of it was, in a free Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> that our Laws did not admit of a negative voice to the King in a Parliament of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and to preſs it now as a Prerogative of all Kings, (beſides the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection it might have upon the rights of our Kingdom,) it might
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110929:21"/> put in the hand of the King a power to deny all, and every one of theſe things, which the Parliaments of both Kingdoms had found neceſſary for the ſetling the peace in all the three Dominions. We marvel not, that the <hi>Warner</hi> here ſhould tax us of a great error, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is the belief of his faction, that every King hath not only a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, but an abſolute affirmative voice in all their Parliaments, as if they were nothing but their arbitrary counſels for to perſwade by their reaſons, but not to conclude nor impede any thing by their Votes; the whole and intire power of making or refuſing Laws being in the Prince alone, &amp; no part of it in the Parliament.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Warners</hi> third challenge againſt us about the ingagement, is, as if the Church had taken upon it to nominate the Officers of the Army; and upon this he makes his invectives. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Church was far from ſeeking power to nominate any one Officer: but the matter was thus; When the State did require of them, what in their judgement would give ſatisfaction to the people, and what would encourage them to go along in the ingagement? one and the laſt part of their anſwer was, that they conceived, if a War ſhall be found neceſſary, much of the peoples encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would depend upon the qualification of the Commanders, to whom the managing of that great truſt ſhould be committed: for after the right ſtating of the War, the next would be the cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of it by ſuch men who had given conſtant proof of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity. To put all the power of the Kingdom in their hand, whoſe by-paſt miſcariages had given juſt occaſion to ſuſpect their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and firmneſs to the intereſt of God before their own or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other mans, would fill the hearts of the people with jealouſies and fears, and how wholſome an advice this was, experience hath now too clearly demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>To make the world know our further reſolutions to meddle with civill affaires, the <hi>Warner</hi> is pleaſed to bring out againſt us above 80 years old ſtories, and all the ſtuff which our malicious enemy, <hi>Spotſwood</hi> can furniſh to him: from this good Author he alledges that our Church diſcharged Merchants to traffique with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and commanded the Change of the market-dayes in <hi>Edenburgh. Anſ.</hi> Both theſe calumnies are taken off at length in the Hiſtorical Vindication. After the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Invaſion in the year 88, many in <hi>Scotland</hi> kept correſpondence with <hi>Spaine,</hi> for treacherous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns: the Inquiſitors did ſeduce ſome, and perſecute others of our
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110929:22"/> Merchants in their traffique, the Church did deale with his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to intercede with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King, for more liberty to our Countrey men in their trading: and in the mean time, while an anſwer was returned from <hi>Madril,</hi> they advertized the people to be wary, how they hazarded their ſouls for any worldly gaine which they could find about the Inquiſitors feet.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Church me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led not with the Munday Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by way of ſupplication in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>As for the Market days, I grant, it was a great grief to the Church, to ſee the Sabbath day profaned by handy labor and journeying, by occaſion of the Munday-markets, in the moſt of the great Towns: for remedy hereof, many ſupplications have been made by the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly to the Parliament: but ſo long as our Biſhops ſate there, theſe petitions of the Church were alwaies eluded: for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates labor in the whole Iſland was to have the ſunday no Sabbath, and to procure by their Doctrine and example, the profanation of that day, by all ſorts of playes, to the end people might be brought back to their old licentiouſneſs and ignorance, by which the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopall Kingdom was advanced. It was viſible in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that the moſt eminent Biſhops were uſual players on the Sabbath, even in time of divine Service. And ſo ſoon as they were caſt out of the Parliament, the Churches ſupplications were granted, and acts obtained for the carefull ſanctification of the Lords day, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of the Markets in all the Land from the <hi>Munday,</hi> to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther days of the week.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Church once for ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Kings life, with the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the cret Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, did call an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note>The <hi>Warners</hi> next challenge of our uſurpation is, the Aſſembly at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> 1567 their ratifying of Acts of Parliament, and ſummoning of all the Countrey to appeare at the next Aſſembly. <hi>Anſ.</hi> If the <hi>Warner</hi> had known the Hiſtory of that time, he would have choſen rathet to have omitted this challenge, then to have proclaimed to the world the great rottenneſs of his own heart; At that time the condition of the Church and Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> was lamentable, the Queen was declared for Popery, King <hi>James</hi> his Father was cruelly, without any cauſe, murthered by the Earl of <hi>Bothwel;</hi> King <hi>James</hi> himſelf in his infancy was very neare to have been deſtroyed by the murtherer of his Father, there was no other way conceivable of ſafety for Religion, for the Infant King, for the Kingdom, but that the Proteſtants ſhould joyn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the defence of King <hi>James</hi> againſt theſe Popiſh murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. For this end, the general Aſſembly did crave conference of the ſecret Counſel: and they with mutual advice did call for a mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110929:22"/> of the whole Proteſtant Party: which did convene at the time appointed moſt frequently, in an extraordinary and mixed aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of al the conſiderable perſons of the Religion, Earls, Lords, Barons, Gentlemen, Burgeſſes, and Miniſters, and ſubſcribed a bond for the revenge of King <hi>Henries</hi> death, and the defence of King <hi>James</hi> his life: This mixed and extraordinary Aſſembly made it one of the chiefe Articles in their bond to defend theſe Acts of the Parliament 1560. concerning Religion, and to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the ratification of them in the next enſuing Parliament. As for the Aſſemblies letter to their Brethren for ſo frequent a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the next extraordinary Aſſembly, it had the Authority of the ſecret Counſel; it was in a time of the greateſt neceſſity, when the Religion and liberties of the land were in evident hazard from the potent and wicked counſels of the Popiſh Party, both at home and abroad; when the life of the young King was dayly in viſible danger, from the hands of them who had murthered his Father, and raviſhed his Mother. Leſſe could not have been done in ſuch a juncture of time by men of wiſdom and courage, who had any love to their Religion, King, and Countrey: but the reſolution of our Prelates is to the contrary, when a moſt wicked villain had obtained the connivance of a Queen to kill her husband, and to make way for the killing of her Son in his Cradle, and after theſe murders to draw a Nation and Church from the true Religion, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by Law, into Popery; and a free Kingdom to an illegal Tyranny; in this caſe there may be no meeting, either of Church, or State, to provide remedies againſt ſuch extraordinary miſchiefs. Beleeve it the <hi>Scots</hi> were never of this opinion.</p>
            <p>What is ſubjoyned to the next Paragraph of our Churches pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to aboliſh Acts of Parliament;<note place="margin">By the laws &amp; cuſtoms of <hi>Scotland</hi> the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly procedes the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mation of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> is but a repetition of what is ſpoken before. Not only the laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and neceſſity refers the ordinary Reformation of errors and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes in Religion to the Eccleſiaſticall Aſſemblies: what they find wrong in the Church, though ratified by acts of Parliament, they rectifie it from the word of God, and thereafter by Petition ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines their rectification to be ratified in a following Parliament, and all former Acts to the contrary to be annulled. This is the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Method of proceeding in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and (as I take it) in all other States and Kingdoms. Were Chriſtians of old hindred to leave Paganiſme and embrace the Goſpel, till the Emperial Laws
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110929:23"/> for Paganiſme, and againſt Chriſtianity were revoked? did the Oecumenical and Nationall Synods of the Ancients ſtay their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of hereſies and corruptions in Religion, till the laws of State (which did countenance theſe errors) were cancelled? Was not Popery in <hi>Germany, France,</hi> and <hi>Britaine,</hi> ſo firmly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, as Civill Laws could do it? It ſeems, the <hi>Warner</hi> here doth joyn with his brother <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> to proclaim all our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers in <hi>Britaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> to be Rebels, for daring by their preachings and Aſſemblies to change theſe things, which by Acts of Parliaments had been approved, before new Parliaments had allowed of their reformation. Nevertheleſs, this plea is fooliſhly intended againſt us, for the Miniſters prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation againſt the Acts of Parliament 1584, eſtabliſhing (in that houre of darkneſs) iniquity by a Law, and againſt the Acts of the Aſſembly of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> declaring the unlawfulneſs of Biſhops and Ceremonies; which ſome Parliaments upon Epiſcopal miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation had approved: both theſe actions of the Church were according to former Laws, and were ratified afterward by Acts of Parliament yet ſtanding in force, which for the <hi>Warner</hi> (a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man, and a ſtranger) to challenge, is to contemn much more groſly the Law, then they do, whom here he is accuſing of that crime.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Church part in the road of Ruthven cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red.</note>By the next Story the <hi>Warner</hi> wil gain nothing, when the true caſe of it is known. In K. <hi>Jame's</hi> minority, one Capt. <hi>James Stuart</hi> did ſo far prevail upon the tender and unexperienced years of the Prince, as to ſteal his countenance unto Acts of the greateſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; ſo far that <hi>James Hamelton,</hi> Earl of <hi>Arran</hi> (the next to the King in blood, in his health a moſt gallant Prince, and a moſt zealous Profeſſor of the true Religion) in time of his ſickneſs, when he was not capable to commit any crime againſt the State, was notwithſtanding ſpoyled of all his livelihood and liberty: his Lands and honor, with the dignity of high Chancelor of <hi>Scotland,</hi> were conferred on that very wicked Tyrant Captain <hi>James,</hi> a number of the beſt affected and prime nobility impatient of ſuch unheard-of oppreſſions, with meer boaſts and no violence at the road of <hi>Ruthven,</hi> chaſed away that unhappy Chancelor from the Kings perſon, this his Majeſty for the time, profeſſed to take in ſo good part, that under his hand he did allow it for good ſervice, in his letters to the moſt of the Neighbor Princes: he dealt alſo with the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110929:23"/> ſecret Counſel, and the chief Judicatories of the Land, and obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from them the approbation of that act of the Lord as conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and laudable, pormiſing likewiſe to ratifie it in the next enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parliament. When the Lords for their more aboundant cleering required the Aſſembles declaration thereupon, the Miniſters decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to meddle at all with the caſe; but the Kings Majeſty ſent his Commiſſioners to the Aſſembly, entreating them withall earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to declare their good liking of that action, which he aſſured them was for his good, and the good both of Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: for their obedience to the Kings importunity, they are here railed upon by the wiſe <hi>Warner.</hi> It is true, Cap. <hi>James</hi> ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter crept in again into Court, and obtained a ſevere revenge againſt the authors of that action, before a Parliament could ſit to approve it, but within a few months the ſame Lords, with ſome more did at <hi>Striveling,</hi> chaſe again that evill man from the Court: whither he never more returned, and this their action was ratified in the next Parliament, and ſo ſtands to this day unqueſtioned by any, but ſuch as the <hi>Warner,</hi> either out of ignorance or malice.</p>
            <p>I am weary to follow the <hi>Warner</hi> in all his wandrings;<note place="margin">The inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the general aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> at the next leap he jumps from the 1584 to the 1648, skipping over in a moment 64 years. The Articles of <hi>Stiveling</hi> mentions that the promoving of the work of Reformation in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> be referred to the general Aſſembly, upon this our friend doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge a flood of his choller: all the matter of his impatience here, is, That <hi>Scotland</hi> when by fraude they had been long allured, and at laſt by open violence invaded by the Engliſh Prelates, that they might take on the yoke of all their corruptiones, they were contented at the earneſt deſire of both the houſes of Parliament, and all the wel-affected in <hi>England,</hi> to aſſiſt their Brethren, to purge out the leaven of Epiſcopacy, and the Service Book, with all the reſt of the old corruptions of the <hi>Engiſh</hi> &amp; <hi>Iriſh</hi> Churches; with the mannaging of this ſo great and good an Eccleſiaſtique work, the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> did intruſt the general aſſembly. No marvail that Dr. <hi>Bramble</hi> a zealous lover of all the <hi>Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, Popery,</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> of which his great Patron Dr. <hi>Lade</hi> ſtands convicted yet without an anſwer to have been bringing in upon the three nations, ſhould be angry at the diſcoverers and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointers of that moſt pious work, as they wont to ſtyle it.</p>
            <p>What here the <hi>Warner</hi> repeats, it is anſwered before, as for
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110929:24"/> the 2 Stories in his concluſion,<note place="margin">The violent apprehen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Maſſe-Prieſts</hi> in their act of Idolatry r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi>
               </note> which he takes out of his falſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>Spots-wood,</hi> adding his own large amplifications; I conceive, there needs no more to be ſaid to the firſt, but that ſome of <hi>John Knocks</hi> zealous hearers, underſtanding of a Maſſe-Prieſt at their very ſide, committing Idolatry contrary to the Laws, did with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence break in upon him, and ſeaſe upon his perſon and Maſſe-cloathes, that they might preſent him to the ordinary Magiſtrate to receive juſtice according to the Law; This act the <hi>Warner</hi> wil have to be a huge Rebellion, not only in the actors, but alſo in <hi>Iohn Knocks,</hi> who was not ſo much as preſent thereat.</p>
            <p>What firſt he ſpeaks of the Aſſemblies convocating the people in arms to be preſent at the tryall of the Popiſh Lords, and their avowing of that their deed to the King in his face, we muſt be pardoned to miſtruſt the <hi>Warner</hi> herein upon his bare word, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the relief of ſome witneſs, and that a more faithfull one, then his Brother in evill, Mr. <hi>Spotſ-wood,</hi> whom yet here he doth not profeſs to cite. Againſt theſe Popiſh Lords after their many trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and bloody murders of the Lieges, the King himſelf at laſt was forced to arme the people; but that the generall Aſſembly did call any unto Arms, we require the <hi>Warners</hi> proof, that we may give it an anſwer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The chief of the Prelates agree with the Presbyterians about the Divine right of Church-iſcipline.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe <hi>Warners</hi> challenge in this Chapter is, That we maintaine our diſcipline by a <hi>Iure divino,</hi> and for this he ſpews out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us a Sea of ſuch Rhetorick, as much better beſeemed <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Aulicus,</hi> then either a <hi>Warner,</hi> or a <hi>Prelate.</hi> In this chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge he is as unhappy as in the reſt, it is for a matter wherein the moſt of his own Brethren (though our Adverſaries) yet fully agree with us, that the diſcipline of the Church is truly by divine right, and that Jeſus Chriſt holds out in Scripture the ſubſtantials of that Government, whereby he will have his houſe to be ruled to the worlds end; leaving the circumſtantials to be determined by the Judicatories of the Church, according to the general rules, which are clear alſo in the word for matters of that nature. In this, neither Papiſts, nor the learned'ſt of the Prelates find any fault with us; yet our <hi>Warner</hi> muſt ſpend a whole Chapter upon it.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:110929:24"/>
            <p>It is true as we obſerved before the elder <hi>Prelates</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Edwards</hi> &amp; <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days, as the <hi>Eraſtians</hi> now, did maintain,<note place="margin">The Warner and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtian bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are obliged by their own principles to adviſe the King to lay aſide Epiſcopacy and ſet up the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery in all his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> that no particular Government of the Church was <hi>jure divino,</hi> and if this be the <hi>Warners</hi> mind, it were ingenuity in him to ſpeak i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out loud, and to endeavor to perſwade his friends about the King, of the truth of this tenet, he was never imployed about a better and more ſeaſonable ſervice: for if the Diſcipline of the Church be but <hi>humano jure,</hi> then Epiſcopacy is kept up upon no conſcience, conſcience being bottomed only upon a divine Right, ſo Epiſcopacy wanting that bottom may well be laid aſide at this time by the King for any thing that concerns conſcience, ſince no Command of God nor Warrant from Scripture ties him to keep it up. This truly ſeems to be the main ground whereupon the whole diſcourſe of this Chapter is builded. Is it tolerable that ſuch truths ſhould be concealed by our <hi>Warners</hi> againſt their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when the ſpeaking of them out might be ſo advantagious to the King and all his Kingdoms; however we with all the reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches do beleeve in our heart the divine Right of Synods and <hi>Preſbyteries,</hi> and for no poſſible inconvenient can be forced to deny or paſs from this part of truth, yet the <hi>Warner</hi> here joyns with the elder <hi>Prelates,</hi> who, till Dr <hi>Banckrofts</hi> advancement to the ſea of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> did unanimouſly deny Epiſcopacy to be of divine Right, and by conſequent affirmed it to be moveable, and ſo lawful to be laid aſide by <hi>Princes,</hi> when ſo ever they found it expedient for their affairs to be quite off it; why doth not the <hi>Warner</hi> and his Brethren ſpeak plainly their thoughts in his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ears? Why do they longer diſſemble their conſcience, only for the ſatisfaction of their ambition, greed and revenge? Sundry of the <hi>Prelatical Divines</hi> come yet further to joyn fully with <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> in denying not only Epiſcopacy, and all other particular forms of Church-Government to be of Divine Inſtitution, but in avowing that no Government in the Church at all is to be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, but ſuch as is a part of the civil power of the Magiſtrate. The <hi>Warner</hi> in the Chapter, and in divers other parts of his Book, ſeems to agree with this judgment; and upon this ground, if he had ingenuity, he would offer his helping hand to unty the bonds of the Kings conſcience, if here it were ſtraitened, by demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from this his principle, that very ſafely without any offence to God, and nothing doubting for conſcience ſake, his Majeſty
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110929:25"/> might lay aſide Epiſcopacy, and ſet up the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> ſo fully as is required in all his Dominions, though not upon a divine Right, which the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> beleeve, yet upon <hi>Eraſtus</hi> royal Right, which the <hi>Warner</hi> here and elſewhere avouches.</p>
            <p>What the <hi>Warner</hi> puts here again upon the <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> the uſurpation of the temporal Sword in what indirect relation ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,<note place="margin">The prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical party were lately bent for Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</note> its probation in the former Chapter was found ſo weak and naughty, that the repetition of it is for no uſe; only we mark that the <hi>Warner</hi> will have the Presbytery to be an abſolute papacy, for no other purpoſe but to vent his deſire of revenge againſt the <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> who gave in a challenge againſt the <hi>Prelates,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the late <hi>Canterburians,</hi> among whom <hi>Doctor Bramble</hi> was one of ſome note, to which none of them have returned to this hour an Anſwer; that their principles unavoidably did bring back the <hi>Pope.</hi> For a <hi>Patriarch</hi> over all the Weſtern Churches, and among all the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> of the whole Catholick Church a primacy in the <hi>Roman,</hi> flows clearly out of the fountain of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, according to the avowed Doctrine of the <hi>Engliſh Prelates,</hi> who yet are more liberal to the <hi>Pope</hi> in granting him, beſide his ſpiritual ſuper-inſpection of the whole Catholick Church, all his temporal Juriſdictions alſo in the patrimony of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and all his other fair principalities within and without <hi>Italy.</hi> There is no Ceremony in <hi>Rome</hi> that theſe men ſtick upon: for of all the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious and idolatrous Ceremonies of <hi>Rome,</hi> their Images, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and Adorations before them are incomparably the worſt; yet the <hi>Warners</hi> friends without any Recantation we have heard of, avow them all, even an Adoration of and to the Altar it ſelf. As for the Doctrines of <hi>Rome,</hi> what points are worſe then theſe which that party have avowed in expreſs terms, a corporal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſts Body upon the Altar, the Tridentine Juſtification, Free-will, final Apoſtacy of the Saints: when no other thing can be anſwered to this our ſore challenge, it is good to put us off with a Squib, that the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> is as abſolute Papacy as ever was in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Preſbyterian Poſition</hi> which the <hi>Warner</hi> here offers, not to diſpute, but to laugh at, That Chriſt, as King of his Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his royal Office and Scepter, hath appointed the Office-bearers and Laws of his Houſe, is accorded to by the moſt and ſharpeſt of our Adverſaries, whether Engliſh or Romiſh, as their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110929:25"/> own tenet: howbeit ſuch fooliſh conſequences, that all acts of Synods muſt be Chriſts Laws, &amp;c. neither they nor we do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg.</p>
            <p>His declamations againſt the novelty of the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> in the ordinary ſtile of the Jeſuits againſt Proteſtants,<note place="margin">The Prelats profeſs now a willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh at leaſt three parts of the for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy.</note> and of the pagan Philoſophers againſt the Chriſtians of old, who will regard? our plea for the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> is, that it is Scriptural; if ſo, it is ancient enough; if not, let it be aboliſhed. But it were good, that here alſo the <hi>Warner</hi> and his friends would be ingenuous, to ſpeak out their minds of Epiſcopacy. Why have they all ſo long deceived the King, in aſſuring him that Engliſh Epiſcopacy was well warranted both by Scripture and antiquity? Be it ſo (which yet is very falſe) that ſomething of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> diſtinct from a <hi>Preſbyter</hi> had any footing in Scripture, yet can they be ſo impudent, as to affirm, that an Engliſh Biſhop in his very fleſh and blood, in his ſubſtantial limbs, was ever known in the world till the <hi>Pope</hi> was become <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt?</hi> A Biſhop by virtue of his office a Lord in <hi>Parliament,</hi> voycing in all Acts of State, and exerciſing the place of a high Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, of a Chancelor, or whatever civil charge the favor of a <hi>Prince</hi> did put upon him; a Biſhop with ſole power of ordination and juriſdiction, without any <hi>Preſbytery;</hi> a Biſhop exerciſing no ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction himſelf in any part of his dioceſs, but devolving the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of that power wholy upon his Officials and Commiſſaries: a Biſhop ordaining <hi>Preſbyters</hi> himſelf alone, or with the faſhional aſſiſtance of any two <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> who chance to be neer; a Biſhop the only paſtor of the whole dioceſs, and yet not bound to feed any flock, either by Word, or Sacrament, or Government, but having a free liberty to devolve all that ſervice upon others, and himſelf to wait at Court ſo many years as he ſhall think fit. This is our Engliſh Biſhop not only in practice but in Law, and ſo was he defended by the great diſputants for <hi>Prelacy</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The portion of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet is ſtu to, cannot be kept upon any principle either of honor or conſcience.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But now let the <hi>Warner</hi> ſpeak out, if any ſuch Biſhop can more be defehded, or was ever known in Scripture, or ſeen in any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church for 800 years and above, after the death of Chriſt. I take it indeed to be Conſcience, that forces now at laſt the beſt of our Court-Divines to deveſt their Biſhop of all civil employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Parliament,</hi> Court, or Kingdom, in denying his ſolitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in ordination, in removing his official and Commiſſary courts, in taking away all his arches, Arch-Biſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Arch-Deacons, Dean
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110929:26"/> and Chapter, &amp;c. in erecting <hi>Preſbyteries</hi> for all ordinations and ſpiritual juriſdiction. It is good that conſcience moves our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries at laſt to come thus far towards us; But why will they not yet come neerer, to acknowledg that by theſe their too lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canted errors they did too long trouble the world; and that the little which yet they deſire to keep of a Biſhop, is nothing leſs then that Engliſh Biſhop, but a new creature of their own deviſing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver known in <hi>England,</hi> which his Majeſty in no honor is obliged to maintain for any reſpect either to the Laws or Cuſtoms of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and leaſt of all, for Conſcience?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt portion of the moſt moderate Epiſcopacy is contrary to Scripture</note>While the <hi>Warner</hi> with ſuch confidence avows, that no text of Scripture can be alledged againſt Epiſcopacy, which may not with more reaſon be applyed againſt the <hi>Preſbytery;</hi> behold I offer him here ſome few, caſting them in a couple of arguments, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his great promiſes, I wiſh he would anſwer at his leaſure.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I do reaſon from <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. all the officers that Chriſt hath appointed in his Church, for the Miniſtry of the Word, are either Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, Prophets, paſtors or Doctors: but Biſhops are none of theſe five: <hi>Ergo,</hi> they are none of the officers appointed by Chriſt for the Miniſtry of the Word. The <hi>major</hi> is not wont to be queſtioned: the <hi>minor</hi> thus I prove; Biſhops are not Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, nor prophets: for its confeſſed, all theſe were extraordinary and temporary Officers: but Biſhops (ſay you) are ordinary and perpetual: our adverſaries pitch upon the fourth, alledging the Epiſcopal office to be paſtoral; but I prove the <hi>Biſhop</hi> no <hi>Paſtor</hi> thus; no <hi>Paſtor</hi> is ſuperior to other <hi>Paſtors</hi> in any ſpiritual power: but according to our adverſary, a <hi>Biſhop</hi> is ſuperior to all the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of his Dioceſs in the power of <hi>ordination</hi> and <hi>juriſdiction. Ergo,</hi> The doubt here is onely of the <hi>major,</hi> which I prove <hi>Argumento à paribus:</hi> no <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is ſuperior to an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> nor an <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> to an <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> nor <hi>Prophet</hi> to a <hi>Prophet,</hi> nor a <hi>Doctor</hi> to a <hi>Doctor,</hi> in any ſpiritual power according to Scripture. <hi>Ergo,</hi> no <hi>paſtor</hi> to a <hi>paſtor.</hi> Again, I reaſon from 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4, 12, 13. What takes the power of <hi>ordination</hi> and <hi>juriſdiction</hi> from <hi>Biſhops,</hi> deſtroys <hi>Biſhops:</hi> as the removal of the ſoul kills the man, and the denyal of the form takes away the ſubject; ſo the power of <hi>ordination</hi> and <hi>juriſdiction,</hi> the eſſential form, whereby the <hi>Biſhop</hi> is conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Preſbyter</hi> and every other Church
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110929:26"/> officer, being removed from him, he muſt periſh: but the quoted places take away clearly theſe powers from the <hi>Biſhop:</hi> for the firſt puts the power of <hi>ordination</hi> in the <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> and a <hi>Biſhop</hi> is not a <hi>Preſbytery;</hi> the ſecond puts the power of <hi>juriſdiction</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi> and the third in a company of men which meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: but the <hi>Biſhop</hi> is not the Church nor a company of men met together: for theſe be many, and he is but one perſon.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Doctors</hi> learning hath ſatified us in theſe two, he ſhall receive more Scriptural arguments againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Prelats unable to anſwer their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites.</note> But why do we expect anſwers from theſe men, when after ſo long time (for all their boaſts of learning and their viſible leaſure) none of their party has had the courage, to offer one word of anſwer to the Scriptures and Fathers, which in great plenty Mr <hi>Parker</hi> and Mr <hi>Didoclave</hi> of old, and of late that miracle of learning moſt noble <hi>Somais,</hi> and that Magazin of antiquity Mr <hi>Blondel</hi> have printed againſt them?</p>
            <p>What in the end of the Chapter the <hi>Warner</hi> adds of our trouble at King <hi>James</hi> his fifty and five queſtions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>96. and of our yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bucklers without any oppoſition till the late unhappy troubles, we anſwer that in this as every where elſe the <hi>Warner</hi> proclaims his great and certain knowledg of our Eccleſiaſtick ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: the troubles of the Scots Divines at that time were very ſmall, for the matter of theſe queſtions, all which they did anſwer ſo roundly, that there was no more ſpeech of them thereafter by the propounders: but the manner and time of theſe queſtions did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed perplex good men, to ſee <hi>Eraſtian</hi> and <hi>Prelatical</hi> counſellors ſo far to prevail with our King, as to make him by captious queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons carp at theſe parts of Church-diſcipline, which by Statutes of Parliament and Acts of Aſſemblies were fully eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Our Church at that time was far from yeelding to <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prelacy was ever grievous to Scotland.</note> great trouble indeed by ſome wicked Stateſ-men was then brought upon the perſons of the moſt able and faithful Miniſters, but our Land was ſo far from receiving of Biſhops at that time, that the queſtion was not ſo much as propoſed to them for many years thereafter, it was in <hi>Ann.</hi> 1606. that the <hi>Engliſh Prelates</hi> did move the <hi>King</hi> by great violence to caſt many of the beſt and moſt learned Preachers of <hi>Scotland</hi> out of their charges, and in <hi>An.</hi> 1610. that a kind of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> was ſet up in the corrupt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of <hi>Glaſgow;</hi> under which the Church of <hi>Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> did heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110929:27"/> groan, till the year 1637. when their burthens was ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by the <hi>Engliſh Prelatical Tax-maſters,</hi> that all was ſhaken off together, and <hi>divine Juſtice</hi> did ſo cloſely follow at the heels, that oppreſſing Prelacy of <hi>England,</hi> as to the great joy of the long oppreſſed <hi>Scots,</hi> that evil root and all its branches was caſt out of <hi>Britain,</hi> where we truſt, no ſhadow of it ſhall ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain be ſeen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Commonwealth is no monſter, when God is made Soveraign, and the commands of men are ſubordinated to the clear will of God.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>HAving cleared the vanity of theſe calumnious challenges, wherewith the <hi>Warner</hi> did animate the <hi>King</hi> and all <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates</hi> againſt the <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> let us try if his skill be any greater, to inflame the people againſt it. He would make the world beleeve that the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> are great tranſubſtantiators of whole Commonwealths into beaſts, and <hi>Metamorphoſers</hi> of whole Kingdoms of men into Serpents with two heads; how great and monſtrous a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erpent muſt the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> be, when ſhe is the mother of a Dragon with two heads? But it is good, that ſhe has nothing to do with the procreation of the Dragon with ſeven heads, the great Antichriſt, the Pope of <hi>Rome:</hi> this honor muſt be left to <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> muſt not pretend to any ſhare in it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">There is no Lordſhip, but a meer ſervice and miniſtry in the Paſtors of the Church.</note>The <hi>Warners</hi> ground for his pretty ſimilitude is, that the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> make two Soveraignties in every Chriſtian ſtate, whoſe commands are contrary. <hi>Anſ.</hi> All the evil lieth in the contrariety of the commands: as for the double Soveraignty, there is no ſhew of truth in it: for the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> cannot be gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty of co-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating two Soveraignties in one State, though the <hi>Prelates</hi> may well be guilty of that fault; ſince they with their Maſters of <hi>Romae</hi> maintain a true Hierarchy, a Spiritual Lordſhip, a domination and principality in their <hi>Biſhops</hi> above all the Members of the Church, but the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> know no <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no Soveraignty in Church Officers, but a meer miniſtry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt. As for the contrariety of commands, its true: Chriſts Miniſters muſt publiſh all the commands of their Soveraign Lord, whereunto no command of any temporal Prince needs or ought to be contrary; but if it fall out to be ſo, it is not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110929:27"/> the Presbytery; but the holy Scriptures which command rather to obey God then man. Dare the <hi>Warner</hi> here oppoſe the <hi>Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians?</hi> dare he maintain a ſubordination of the Church to the State in ſuch a faſhion, that the clear commands of God, publiſhed by the Church, ought to give place to the contrary commands of the State? If the <hi>Warner</hi> muſt needs invert and contradict Chriſt his ruling of this caſe, let him go on to preach doctrin pointblank con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Apoſtles, that it is better to obey men then God. It falls out as rarely in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as any where in the world, that the Church and State run contrary ways; but if it ſo happen, the common rules of humane direction towards right and wrong judgment muſt be followed: if a man find either the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or the State, or both, command what he knows to be wrong (for neither the one nor the other hath any infallibility) there is no doubt, but either or both may be diſobeyed, yet with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that for diſobedience to the Churches moſt juſt commands, a man cannot fall under the ſmalleſt temporal inconvenience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the States good pleaſure, but for his diſobedience to the moſt unjuſt commands of the State, he muſt ſuffer what ever puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the law doth inflict, without any relief from the Church.</p>
            <p>Two inſtances are brought by the <hi>Warner,</hi> of the Church and States contrary commands: the firſt the King commanded <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> to feaſt the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadors, but the Church comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Edenburgh</hi> to faſt that day when the King deſired them to feaſt. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here were no ſo contrary commands, but both were obeyed, the people did keep the humiliation, and ſome of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates that ſame day did give the banquet to the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors as the King commanded; that for this any Church cenſure was intended againſt them, it is a malicious calumny, according to the author of this fable his own confeſſion, as at length may be ſeen in the unloading of <hi>Iſſachars</hi> burden.</p>
            <p>As for his ſecond inſtance,<note place="margin">The <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> is full of calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths.</note> the difference of the Church and State about the late ingagement, we have ſpoken to it in the former Chapter at length: the furtheſt the Church went, was by humble petitions and remonſtrances to ſet before the Parliament the great danger, which that ingagement (as it was ſtated and managed) did portend to Religion, the Kings perſon and whole Kingdom, when contrary to their wholeſom advices the ingagement went on, they medled not to oppoſe the act of State, further then to declare their judgment of its unlawfulneſs, according to the duty of faithful
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110929:28"/> watchmen, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. It is very falſe that the Church have chaſed any man out of the Countrey, or excommunicated any for follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that engagement, or have put any man to ſackcloath for it, unto this day. Neither did ever any man call the freedome of the late Parliament in queſtion, how unſatisfied ſoever many were with its proceedings.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Warner</hi> heaps up ſo many untruths in a few lines, in things done but yeſterday before the eyes of thouſand, we ſhal not wonder of his venturing to lye confidently in things paſt long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any now living were born: but there are a generation of men who are bold to ſpeak what makes for their end, upon the hope that few will be at the pains, to bring back what hath flown from their teeth to the touchſtone of any ſolid triall.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. X.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The nature of the Preſbytery is very concordant with Parliament.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN the 10 Chapter the <hi>Warner</hi> undertakes to ſhew the antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Presbyteries to Parliaments; albeit there be no greater harmony poſſible betwixt any two bodies, then betwixt a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſembly and Parliament, a Presbytery and an inferiour Civil Court, if either the conſtitution, or end, or dayly practiſe of theſe judicatories be looked upon: but the Prelatical learning is of ſo high a flight, that it dares undertake to prove any concluſion, yet theſe men are not the firſt, that have offered to force men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve upon unanſwerable arguments, though contrary to common ſence &amp; reaſon, that ſnow is black, the fire cold, and the light dark.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The eight deſires of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church about the ingagement were juſt and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</note>For the proof of his concluſion, he brings back yet again the late engagement: how often ſhall this inſipide Colwort be ſet upon our table? Will the <hi>Warner</hi> never be filled with this unſavoury diſh? The firſt crime that here the <hi>Warner</hi> marks in our Church againſt the late Parliament in the matter of the ingagement is, their paper of the eight deſires: upon this he vapoureth out all his good pleaſure, not willing to know that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe deſires were drawn from the Church by the <hi>Parliaments</hi> own meſſages, and that wel-neer all theſe deſires were counted by the <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelf to be very juſt and neceſſary: Eſpecially theſe two which the wiſe <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> pitches upon, as moſt abſurd, for the firſt a ſecurity to religion from the King, upon oath under his hand and ſeal: here the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among us was not for the thing it ſelf, but only about the time,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110929:28"/> the order, and ſome part of the matter of that ſecurity. And for the ſecond, the quallification of the perſons to be imployed, that all ſhould be ſuch who had given no juſt cauſe of Jealouſie; no man did queſtion, but all who were to have the managing of that war ſhould be free of all juſt cauſes of Jealouſie, which could be made appear not to half a dozen of Miniſters, but to any competent judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory according to the laws of the Kingdom. The <hi>Warner</hi> hath not been careful to inform himſelf, where the knot of the difference lay, and ſo gives out his own groundleſs conjectures, for true Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical narrations, which he might eaſily have helped by a more attentive reading of our publick Declarations.</p>
            <p>The ſecond fault he finds with our Church is, that they proclaim in print their diſ-ſatisfaction with that ingagement,<note place="margin">It is one of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> to publiſh declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> as favourable to the malignant Party, &amp;c. <hi>Anſ.</hi> The <hi>Warner</hi> knows not that it is one of the liberties of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> eſtabliſhed by law and long cuſtom, to keep the people by publick Declarations in their duty to God, when men are like to draw them away to ſin, according to that of <hi>Eſay</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 12, 13. What in great humility, piety, and wiſdom was ſpoken to the world in the declaration of the Church concerning that undertaking, was viſible enough for the time to any, who were not peremptory to follow their own ways: and the lamentable event ſince hath opened the eyes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who before would not ſee, to acknowledge their former er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors: but if God ſhould ſpeak never ſo loud from heaven, the <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> and his Party will ſtop their ears: for they are men of ſuch gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Spirits, as ſcorn to ſubmit either to God or men, but in a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> conſtancy they will be ever the ſame, though their counſels and ways be found never ſo palpably pernicious.</p>
            <p>The third thing the <hi>Warner</hi> lays to the charge of our Church is,<note place="margin">The leavy was never off red to be ſtopped by the Church.</note> that they retarded the leavies. <hi>Anſ.</hi> In this alſo the <hi>Warner</hi> ſhews his ignorance or malice: for how ſore ſoever the leavy (as then ſtated and mannaged) was againſt the hearts of the Church, yet their oppoſition to it, was ſo cold-rife and ſmal, that no complaint needs be made of any retardment from them. So ſoon as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders thought it expedient, there was an Army gotten up ſo numerous and ſtrong, that with the ordinary bleſſing of God was abundantly able to have done all the profeſſed ſervice: but where the averſion of the hearts of the Church, and the want of their prayers is ſuperciliouſly contemned, what marvell, that the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt arm of fleſh be quickly broken in pieces?</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:110929:29"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Church was not the cauſe of the gathering at <hi>Mauchlin-Moor.</hi>
               </note>The fourth Charge is moſt calumnious, That the Church ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the Country together in Arms at <hi>Mauchlin-Moor</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Expedition, <hi>Anſ.</hi> No Church-man was the cauſe of that meeting, a number of Yeomen being frighted from their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, did fly away to that corner of the Land, that they might not be forced againſt their conſcience to go as Souldiers to <hi>England:</hi> while their number did grow, and they did abide in a Body for the ſecurity of their perſons, upon a ſudden a part of the Army came upon them; ſome Miniſters being near (by occaſion of the Communion at <hi>Mauchlin</hi> the day before) were good Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with the people to go away in peace. And when the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was tryed to the bottom by the moſt Eagle-eyed of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> nothing could be found contrary to the Miniſters Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, that they were no ways the cauſe of the peoples convening or fighting at <hi>Mauchlin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Aſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly is help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and not hurtful to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </note>The paralel that the <hi>Warner</hi> makes betwixt the general Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and <hi>Parliament</hi> is malicious in all its parts. For the firſt, though the one Court be Civil, and the other Spiritual, yet the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> lay the Authority of both upon a divine Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that for conſcience ſake the Courts Civil muſt be obeyed in all their lawful Commands, as well as the Aſſemblies of the Church; God being the Author of the politick Order as well as the Eccleſiaſtick, and the revenger of the contempt of the one as well as the other. But what doth the <hi>Warner</hi> mean, to mock at Miniſters for carrying themſelves as the Embaſſadors of Chriſt, for judging according to the rule of Scripture, for caring for life eternal? Is he become ſo ſhamefully impious, as to perſwade Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to give over the care of life eternal, to lay aſide the holy Scripture, and deny their embaſſage from Jeſus Chriſt? Behold, what Spirit leads our <hi>Prelates,</hi> while they jeer the World out of all Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gion, and chaſe away Miniſters from Chriſt, from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from eternal Life.</p>
            <p>Of the ſecond part of the Paralel, That people are more ready to obey their Miniſters then their Magiſtrates, what ſhall be made? All the power which Miniſters have with the people is builded on their love to God and Religion: how much ſoever it is, a good Stateſman will not envy it; for he knows that God and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience conſtrain Miniſters to employ all the power they have with the people to the good of the Magiſtrate, as the Deputy and Servant of God for the peoples true good. The <hi>Warner</hi> here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110929:29"/> beſt his own meaning, while he ſcoffs at Miniſters for their threatning of men with hells fire. Are our <hi>Prelates</hi> come to ſuch open <hi>Proclamations</hi> of their <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> as to print their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to baniſh out of the hearts of people all fear, not only of Church-Cenſures, but even of hell it ſelf? Whither may not Satan drive at laſt the Inſtruments of his Kingdom?</p>
            <p>The third part of the Paralel conſiſts of a number of unjuſt and falſe Imputations before particularly refuted.</p>
            <p>What he ſubjoyns of the power of the general Aſſembly to name Committees to ſit in the Intervals of Aſſemblies,<note place="margin">The ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees is a right of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Court, as well Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick as Civil.</note> it is but a poor Charge: Is it not the dayly practiſe of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> to nominate their Committees of State for the Intervals of <hi>Parliament?</hi> Is it not one inherent right to every Court to name ſome of their number to cognoſce upon things within their own ſphere at what ever times the Court it ſelf finds expedient? however the Judicatories of the Church by the Laws of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom being authorized to meet when themſelves think fit both or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily and <hi>pro renata,</hi> their power of appointing Committees for their own Affairs was never queſtioned: and truly theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees in the times of our late troubles, when many were lying in wait to diſturb both Church and State, have been forced to meet oftner then otherwiſe any of their Members did deſire; whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion from their particular Charges (though for attendance on the publick) is joyned with ſo great faſhery and expence, that with all their heart they could be glad to decline it, if fear of detriment to the Church made not theſe meetings very neceſſary.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Preſbytery is no burden to any honeſt man.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe bounds and compaſs of the <hi>Warners</hi> rage againſt the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> is very large;<note place="margin">There is no rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur at all in the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery.</note> not being content to have incenſed the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt it, he comes down to the body of the people, and will have them beleeve the ſpecial enmity of the <hi>Scots Diſcipline</hi> againſt them, firſt becauſe it inflicts Church-Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures upon every one for the ſmalleſt faults. <hi>Anſ.</hi> The faults which the <hi>Warner</hi> mentions may well be an occaſion of a private advice in the ear, but that any of them did ever procure the ſmalleſt cenſure of the Church, it is a great untruth: no man who knows us, will complain of our rigour; here we wiſh we were able to refute upon as good reaſon the charge of our laxneſs in the mouth of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> as we are that of our ſtrictneſs in the mouth
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:110929:30"/> of <hi>Erastians.</hi> We would know of the <hi>Warner,</hi> what are theſe Sabbath Recreations, which he ſaith are void of ſcandal, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the duties of the day; are they not the ſtage plays, and the other honeſt paſtimes, wherewith his friends were wont to ſanctifie the Lords Day, as no more a Sabbath, then any other day in the year, and much leſs then diverſe Popiſh Feſtivals? An Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteme in the loweſt gut will ſhew it ſelf by the unſavory vapors, which now and then are eructate from it. That ever in <hi>Scotland</hi> there was one word of debate about Starch and Cuffs, is more then the <hi>Warner</hi> can prove.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Crimes till repented of ought to keep from the holy table.</note>The ſecond oppreſſion whereby the <hi>Preſbytery</hi> treads the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under foot, is a rare cruelty, That perſons, for grievous crimes, whereof the Magiſtrate takes notice, are called to Eccleſiaſtick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Will the <hi>Doctor</hi> in his fury againſt us, run out upon all his own friends for no appearance of a fault? Will either the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> or <hi>Popiſh Prelates</hi> admit Murderers, Whores or Theeves to the holy Table without any ſigns of repentance? Is not the greateſt crime the ground of the greateſt ſcandal? Shall ſmall ſcandals be purged away by repentance, and the greateſt be totally paſt by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> The <hi>Warner</hi> here may know his own meaning, but others will confeſs their ignorance of his mind.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cation in <hi>Scotland</hi> is not inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to any.</note>The third grievance he would have the people conceive againſt the <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> is, The rigour of their excommunication; in this alſo the <hi>Warner</hi> ſeems to know little of the <hi>Scots</hi> way; let ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication be ſo ſevere in <hi>Scotland</hi> as is poſſible, yet the hurt of it is but ſmall: It is ſo rare an accident, men may live long in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and all their life never ſee that Cenſure executed; I have lived in one of the greateſt Cities of that Land, and for forty ſeven years even from my birth to this day, that Cenſure to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg or hearing was never executed there in my days but twice; firſt upon one obſtinate and very prophane <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and next on ſome horrible ſcandalous <hi>Prelates.</hi> Again, when any is excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated by the Church, we go no further with them then <hi>Pauls</hi> command, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14. only they who are not tyed to them by natural bonds, abſtain from familiar and unneceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, to bring them by the ſence of this ſhame to repentance for their ſins. Thirdly, The civil inconveniences which follow that Cenſure, come along from the State, and the Acts of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> for which the Church ought not to be challenged, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by <hi>Prelates,</hi> who wont to allow their Officials to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110929:30"/> whole incorporations of people for a ſmall debt of mony, and to preſſe the contemners of that frivolous and profane ſentence, with all the civill inconveniences they could. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what ever be the lawes in Scotland, againſt them who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long in the contempt of Excommunication, (which is not inflicted but for great ſins, and after a long proceſſe) yet certainly their executon is very farre from all cruelty, as they who know the proceedings of that land, will beare witneſſe.</p>
            <p>What he objects about fugitives; it is true, when a proceſſe is begunne, a fugitive may have it concluded, and ſent after him; but we count not that man a fugitive from diſcipline or contumacious as the Warner quarrels us, who upon juſt feare to hazard his life does not compear.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Preſbytery is hurtfull to no order of men.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>PRaelaticall malice is exorbitant beyond the bounds of all ſhew of moderation:<note place="margin">The warners outrage againſt the Presbytery</note> was it not enough to have calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the Presbytery to Kings, Princes and Soveraignes, to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and all Courts of Juſtice, to people and all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons? but yet a new chapter muſt be made to ſhew in it the hurtfulneſſe of Presbytery to all orders of men: we muſt have patience to ſtand a little in the unſavoury aire of this vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit alſo.</p>
            <p>Unto the nobility and gentry the Presbytery muſt be hurtfull,<note place="margin">The Praelates were conſtant oppreſſors of the Nobility and gentry.</note> becauſe it ſubjecteth them to the cenſures of a raw heady novice and a few ignorant artificers. Anſ. Its good that our praelats are now turned pleaders againſt the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Nobility and gentry: its not long ſince the praelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal clergy were accuſtomed to ſet their foule feet on the necks of the greateſt peeres of the three Kingdomes, with ſo high a pride and preſſure; that to ſhake of their yoks, no ſuffering, no hazard has beene refuſed by the beſt of the Nobility, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110929:31"/> gentry of <hi>Britaine:</hi> but natures and principles are ſo eaſy to be changed, that no man now needs feare any more oppreſſion from the praelates, though they were ſet downe againe and well warmed in their repaired thrones.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The way of the Scotes Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably better then that of the Engliſh E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy.</note>But to the challenge we anſwer, that the meaneſt Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of a ſmall Congregation in Scotland conſiſts of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, and a dozen (at leaſt) of the moſt wiſe, pious and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that are to be found in the whole flock; which yet the Warner here makes to be judges but of the common people in matters of ſmalleſt moment. But for the claſſicall Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, to which he referres the Eccleſiaſticall cauſes of the Nobility and gentry, and before whom indeed every Church proceſſe of any conſiderable weight or difficulty does come, though it concern the perſons of the meaneſt of the people, this Presbytery does conſiſt ordinarily of fifeteene Miniſters (at leaſt) and fifeteen of the moſt qualified noblemen, gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemen and Burgeſſes, which the circuit of fifteen pariſhes can afford; theſe (I hope) may make up a judicatory of a great deale more worth then any officiall court, which conſiſts but of one judge, a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tty mercenary lawyer, to whoſe care alone the whole Eccleſiaſtick jurisdiction over all the Nobility and gentry of divers ſhires is committed, and that without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale as the Warner has told us, except it be to a Court of delegates; a miſerable reliefe that all the Nobility, Gentry, and Commons of a Kingdome, who are oppreſſed by Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall officials, have no other remedy but to goe attend a Committee of two or three civilians at London, deputed for the diſcuſſing of ſuch appeales.</p>
            <p>The Presbyterian courſe is much more ready, ſolide and equitable: if any grievance ariſe from the ſentence of a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, a Synode twice a yeare doth ſit in the bounds, and attends for a weeke, or if need be, longer, to determine all appeales, and redreſſe all grievances: now the Synode does conſiſt of all the Miniſters within the bounds, which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily are of diverſe whole ſhires, as that of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> of the upper and nearer ward of <hi>Clidſedaile, Baerranfrow, Lennox, Kile, Carrick</hi> and <hi>Cunninghame;</hi> alſo beſide Miniſters, the conſtant Members who have deciſive voyce in Synodes, are
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110929:31"/> the chiefe Noblemen, Gentlemen and Burgeſſes of all theſe ſhires, among whom their be ſuch parts for judgement as are not to be found nor expected in any inferiour civill Court of the Kingdome; yet if it fall out ſo, that any party be grieved with the ſentence of a Synode, there is then a farther and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall appeale to a Generall aſſembly, which conſiſt of as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Burgeſſes and more Gentlemen from every shire of the Kingdome, then come to any Parliament: Beſides the prime Nobility and choiſeſt Miniſtry of the land; having the Kings Majeſtie in perſon, or in his abſence, his high Commiſſioner to be their praeſident. This meeting yeerly (or oftner; if need be) ſits ordinarily a month; and if they thinke fit, lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: the number, the wiſedome, the eminency of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Court is ſo great, that beſide the unjuſtice, it were a very needleſſe labour to appeal from it to the Parliament, for (as we have ſaid) the King or his high Commiſſioner, ſits in both meetings, albeit in a different capacity: the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and qualification of Knights and Burgeſſes is ever large, as great in the aſſembly, as in Parliament: onely the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is, that in Parliament all the Nobility in the Kingdome ſit without any election, and by vertue of their birth, but in the Aſſembly onely who for age, wiſedome and pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the Presbyteries as fitteſt to judge in Eccleſiaſtick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, but to make up this odds of the abſence of ſome No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen, the aſſembly is alwaies adorned with above an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the choiſeſt Paſtors of the whole land, none whereof may ſit in Parliament: nothing that can conciliate authority to a Court, which can be found in the Nation, is wanting to the generall aſſembly; how baſely ſo ever our praelats are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to trample upon it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond alleadged hurt,<note place="margin">All queſtions about pattro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land are now ended.</note> which the Nobility have from the Presbytery, is the loſſe of their partonages by congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions electing their Paſtors. Anſw. However the judgement of our Church about pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onages, is no other then that of the Reformed divines abroad, yet have our Presbyteries alw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies with patience, endured patrons to preſent unto vacant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, till the Parliament now at laſt hath taken away that grievance.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:110929:32"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The poſſeſſors of Church-l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver feared for Biſhops, but never for the Presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery.</note>The Nobilities next hurt by the Presbytery, is their loſſe of all their impropriations and Abey-lands, Anſ. How Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck an accuſation is this? for who knowes not how farre the whole generation of the praelaticke faction doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the higheſt of the Presbyterians in zeale againſt that which they call Sacriledge? never any of the Presbyterians did attempt either by violence, or a courſe of Law, to put out any of the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bility or Gentry from their poſſeſſions of the Chu ch-lands, but very lately the threats and vigorous activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the p aelats, and their followers were ſo vehement in this kinde, that all the Nobility and Gentry who had any intereſt, were wackned (to purpoſe) to take heed of their rights. In the laſt Parliament of Scotland when the power of the Church was as great as they expect to ſee it again, though they obtained the abolition of patronages, yet were the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of the Church-lands and tythes ſo little harmed, that their rights thereto were more cleerly and ſtrongly confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then by any praeceding Parliament.</p>
            <p>The fourth hurt is that every ordinary Presbyter will make himſelfe a Noblemans fellow. Anſ. No where in the World doe gracious Miniſters (though meane borne men) receive more reſpect from the Nobility then in Scotland: neither any where does the Nobility and Gentry receive more duely their honour then from the Miniſters there. That inſolent ſpeech fathered on Mr. <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> is demonſtrat to be a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous calumny in the hiſtoricall vindication.</p>
            <p>However the Warner may know that in all Europe where Biſhops have place, it has ever (at leaſt theſe 800 yeares) beene their nature to trample under foot, the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gheſt of the Nobility. As the Pope muſt be above the Emperour, ſo a little Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin</hi> can tell to King <hi>James,</hi> that he may well he counted a companion of any Ilander King: were the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in Scotland ever content, till they got in Parliament, the right hand and the neareſt ſeates to the throne, and the doore of the greateſt Earles, Marqueſſes and Dukes? was it not Epiſcopacy, that did advance poore and capricious Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants to ſtrive for the white ſtaves and great Seales of both Kingdomes, with the prime Nobility; and often overcome
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:110929:32"/> them in that ſtrife? In <hi>Scotland</hi> I know, and the Warner will aſſure for <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> that the baſeſt borne of his Brethren has ruffled it in the ſecret councell, in the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Exchequer, in the higheſt Courts of Juſtice, with the greateſt Lords of the Land: its not ſo long, that yet it can be forgotten, ſince a Biſhop of <hi>Galloway</hi> had the modeſty to give unto a Marqueſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gile, tantum non</hi> a broad lye in his face at the Councell table. The Warner ſhall do well to reckon no more with Presbyters for braving of Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>The nixt hee will have to be wronged by the Presbytery are the Orthodox Clergy.<note place="margin">The Prelat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> continue to annull the being of all the Reformed Churches for their want of Epiſcopacy.</note> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All the Presbyterians to him (it ſeemes) are heterodoxe; Epiſcopacy is ſo neceſſary a truth that who denies it, muſt be ſtamped as for a grievous errour with the character of heterodox. The following words cleere this to be his minde, <hi>they l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>the comfortable aſſurance of undoubted ſucceſſion by Epiſcopall ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation:</hi> what ſence can be made of theſe words, but that all Miniſters who are not ordained by Biſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, muſt lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the comfortleſſe uncertainty of any lawfull ſucceſſion in their Miniſteriall charge, for want of this ſucceſſion through the lineall deſcent of Biſhops from the Apoſtles; at leaſt for want of ordination by the hands of Biſhops, as if unto them onely the power of miſſion and ordination to the Miniſtry were committed by Chriſt? becauſe of this defect the Presbyterian Miniſters muſt not onely want the comfort of an aſſured and undoubted calling to the Miniſtery, but may very well know and bee aſſured that their calling and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery is null. The words immediatly following are ſcrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out after their Printing: for what cauſe the Author beſt knoweth: but the purpoſe in hand makes it probable, that the deletted words did expreſſe more of his minde, then it was ſafe in this time and place to ſpeake out: it was the late Doctrine of Doctor <hi>Brambles</hi> prime friends, that the want of Epiſcopall ordination did ot onely annull the calling of all the Miniſters of <hi>France, Holland, Zwit-zerland,</hi> and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> but alſo did hinder all theſe Societies to bee true Churches: for that popular Sophiſme of the Jeſuits our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110929:33"/> did greedily ſwallow; where are no true Sacrament, there is no true Church; and where is no true Miniſtry, there are no true Sacraments; and where no true ordination, there is no true Miniſtry; and where no Biſhops, there in no true ordination; and ſo in no reformed Country but in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> where were true Biſhops, is any true Church. When Epiſcopacy comes to this height of elevation, that the want of it muſt annull the Miniſtry, yea the very being of all the Reformed Churches at one ſtrock, is it any marvell, that all of them do concurre together for their own preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to aboliſh this inſolent abaddon and deſtroyer? and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all its ruine have yet no diſcomfort at all, nor any the leaſt doubt of their moſt lawfull ordination by the hands of the Presbytery.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Prelats are ſo baſely injurious to all the Reformed Churches that their ſelfes are aſhamed of it</note>After all this was written, as here it ſtands, another copy of the Warners book was brought to my hand, wherin <hi>I found the deleted line ſtand Printed in theſe diſtinct termes, and put it to a dangerous queſtion whether it be within the payle of the Church,</hi> the deciphering of theſe words puts it beyond all peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that what I did conjecture of the Warner and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns minde, of the ſtate of all the reformed Churches, was no mis-take, but that they do truely judge the want of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall Ordination to exclude all the Miniſters of other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, and their flocks alſo from the lines of the true Church. This indeed is a moſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngerous queſtion: for it ſtricks at the root of all. If the Warner out of remorſe of conſcience had blotted out of his booke that errour, the Repentance had beene commendable: But hee has left ſo much yet behind unſcraped out, as does ſhew his minde to continue what it was, ſo that feare alone to provoke the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed here at this unſeaſonable time, ſeemes to have been the cauſe of deleting theſe too cleare expreſſions of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall tenent againſt the very being and ſubſiſtence of all the Proteſtant Churches which want Epiſcopacy, where theſe men doe ſtill ſtand upon the extreme pinacle of impudency and arrogance, denying the Reformed to be true Churches, and without ſcruple averring <hi>Rome</hi> as ſhee ſtands this day, under the councell of Trent, to be a Church moſt true, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:110929:33"/> there is an eaſy way of ſalvation, from which all ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion is needleſſe, and with which a re-union were much to be deſired? That gracious faction this day is willing enough to perſwade, or at leaſt to reſt content without any oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the King ſhould of himſelfe without and before a Parliament, (though contrary to many ſtanding Lawes) grant under his hand and ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a full liberty of Religion to the bloudy <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and to put in their hands, both armes, Caſtles and prime Places of truſt in the State; that the King ſhould give aſſurance of his endeavour, to get all theſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in the next Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> theſe men can heare with all moderation and patience: but behold their fu ious impatience, their whole art and induſtry is wakned, when they heare of any appearance of the Kings inclination to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards covenanting Proteſtants: night and day they beate in his Majeſties head, that all the miſchiefes of the World doe lurke in that miſerable Covenant, that de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th and any misfortune, that the ruine of all the Kingdomes ought much rather to be imbraced by His Majeſty, then that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Monſter, that very hell of the Covenant, becauſe for ſooth it doth oblige in plaine termes the taker to endeavour (in his ſtation) the abolition of their great Goddeſſe, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy.</p>
            <p>The next hurt of Miniſters from the Presbytry, is,<note place="margin">The generality of Epiſcopall Clergy have ever been co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with ignorance, beggery, and contempt.</note> that by it they are brought to ignorance, contempt and beggery. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Whither Epiſcopacy or Presbytry is the fitteſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to avert theſe evills, let reaſon or experience teach men to judge. The P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>esbyteriall diſcipline doth oblige to a great deale of ſeverer tryalls in all ſort of learning requiſite in a divine before ordination then doth the Epiſcopall: let either the rule or practiſe of Presbyterian and Epiſcopall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination be compared or the weekly Exerciſes and monthly diſputations in Latine upon the controverted heads be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon which the Presbytery exacts of every Miniſter after his ordination all the dayes of his life: for experience, let the <hi>French, Dutch</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> divines who have beene or yet are, be compared with the ordinary Generation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy, and it will be found, that the Prelates have not great
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:110929:34"/> reaſon ſo ſuperciliouſly to looke downe with contempt upon their Brethrens learning. I hope, <hi>Cartwright, Whitaker, Perkins, Reynolds, Parker, Ames,</hi> and other Presbyterian <hi>Engliſh</hi> were inferior in learning to none of their oppoſits: ſome of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Biſhops have not wanted good ſtore of learning, but the moſt of them (I believe) will be content to leave of boaſting in this ſubject; what does the Warner ſpeak to us of ignorance, contempt and Beggery? does not all the World know, that albeit ſome few, ſcarce one of twenty, did brooke good benefices, yea plurality of them whereby to live in ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor at Court, or where they liſted in their non-reſidency, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe it hath bin much complained, that the greateſt part of the Prieſts, who have the cure of the ſoules thorow all the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> were incomparably the moſt ignorant, beggerly and contemptible Clergy, that ever have bin ſeen in any of the reformed Churches? neither did we ever heare of any great ſtudy in the Prelats to remedy theſe evills, albeit ſome of them be provider t enough for their owne Families. Doctor <hi>Bramble</hi> knowes who had the skill before they had ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſeven yeare in their chaire to purchaſe above fifteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds a year for themſelves and their heirs what ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Prelats continue to hate preaching and prayer but to idolize a popiſh ſervice.</note>The third evill which the Presbytery brings upon Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is, that it makes them prate, and pray nonſence everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is indeed a great heartbreake unto ignorant, lazy and unconſciencious Miniſters to be put to the paines of Preaching and Prayer, when a read ſervice was wont to be all their exerciſe: but we thought th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t all indifferently ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men had long agoe bin put from ſuch impudence. It was the late labour of the Prelats by all their skill to diſgrace Preaching and Praying without booke, to cry up the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy at the only ſervice of God, and to idolize it as a moſt Heavenly and Divine peece of write, which yet is nought but a Tranſcript of the ſuperſtitious breviary and idolatrous miſſall of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Warner would doe well to conſider and anſwer after ſeven years adviſement Mr <hi>Bailie</hi> his para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of the Service Booke with the Miſſall and Breviary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he preſent the world with new paralells of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:110929:34"/> liturgy, with the directories of the Rerormed Churches. It is ſo indeed, that all Preaching and Praying without Booke is but a pratting of non-ſence everlaſtingly; why then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues the King and many well minded men to be deceived by our Doctors, while they affirme that they are as much for Preaching in their practiſe and opinion as the Presbyterians, and for Prayer without book alſo, before and after Sermon, and in many other occaſions? it ſeemes theſe affi mations are nothing but groſſe diſſimulation in this time of their low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and affliction, to decline the envy of people againſt them for their profane contempt of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vine ordinances; for we may ſee here their tenet to remaine what it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and themſelves ready enough, when their ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on ſhall be fitter, to ring it out loud in the eares of the World, that for Divine Service people needs no more but the reading of the Liturgy, that Sermons on week dayes and Sundayes afternoon muſt all be laid aſide,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide laden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium.</hi> cap. 7.</note> that on the Sabbath before noone Sermon is needleſſe, and from the mouths of the moſt Preachers very noxious; that when ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned Schollars are pleaſed on ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e feſtivall dayes to have an Oration, it wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld be ſhort and according to the Court paterne, without all Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rit and life for edification; but by all meanes it muſt be provided, that no word of prayer either before or after be ſpoken, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only a bidding to pray for many things, even for the welfare of the ſoules departed; and all this alone in the words of the Lords Prayer. If any ſhall dare to expreſſe the deſi es of his heart to God in privat or publick in any words of his o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n framing, he is a groſſe Puritan, who is bold to offe to God his own nonſence rather then the ancient, and well adviſed prayers of the holy Church.</p>
            <p>The Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ner is here alſo miſtaken in his beliefe, that ever the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> had any Liturgy; they had and have ſtill ſome formes for helpe and direction, but notice e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er in any of them by Law or practiſe: they do not condemne the uſe of ſet formes for Rules, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t for uſe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, who are thereby endeavouring to attaine a readineſſe to pray in their family our of their own heart in the words which Gods Spirit dytes to them; but for Miniſters to ſuppreſſe their moſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:110929:35"/> comfortable and uſefull gift of prayer by tying their mouth unto ſuch formes which themſelves or others have compoſed we count it a wrong to the giver, and to him who has received the gift, and to the Church for whoſe uſe that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Epiſcopall Warrants for clandeſtin marriages, rob Parents of their child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note>In the next place the Warner makes the Presbytry injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to parents, by marying their children contrary to their conſent, and forcing them to give to the d ſobedient as large a portion as to any other of their obedient children, and than it is no marvail the <hi>Scots</hi> ſhould doe theſe things who have ſtripped the King the father of their Country of his juſt rights. <hi>Anſ.</hi> By the Warners Rule all the actions of a Nation where a Presbyte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y lodges muſt be charged on the back of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery. <hi>II.</hi> The Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> denyes, that they have ſtripped the King of his juſt Rights; while he was ſtirred up and keeped on by the prelaticall faction to courſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to himſelfe and all his people; after their ſhedding of much bloud, before the exerciſe of all parts of his Royall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, they onely required for all ſatisfaction and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to Religion and Liberties, the grant of ſome few moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable demands. The unhappy Prelats from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our troubles to this day finding our great demande to runne upon the abolition of their Office, did ever preſſe His Majeſty to deny us that ſatisfaction, and rather then Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſhould be laid aſide, they have concluded that the King himſelfe, and all his family and all his three Kingdomes ſhall periſh: yet with all patience the <hi>Scots</hi> contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to ſupplicate and to offer not onely their Kingdome, but their lives and eſtates and all they have for His M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>je <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vice upon the grant of their few and eaſy demands, but no miſery e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther of King or people can overcome the deſperate obſtinacy of Prelaticall hearts.</p>
            <p>As for parents co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to the mariage of their childre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, how tenderly it is provided for in <hi>England,</hi> it may be ſeen at length in the very place cited. It was the Biſhops, who by their warrants for clandeſtine mariages, and diſpenſations with mariages without warrant have ſpoyled many parents of their deare children: with ſuch abhominations the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110929:35"/> was never acquainted; all that is alleadged out of that place of our diſcipline, is, when a cruel parent or tutor abuſes their authority over their Children, and againſt all reaſon for their owne evill ends, perverſely will croſſe their Children in their lawfull and every way honeſt deſires of mariage; that in that caſe the Magiſtrates and Miniſters may be intreated by the grieved childe to deale with the unjuſt parent or tutor, that by their meditation reaſon may be done. I beleeve this advice is ſo full of equity, that no Church nor State in the world will complaine of it: but how ever it be, this caſe is ſo rare in <hi>Scotland</hi> that I profeſſe, I never in my life did know, nor did hear of any childe before my dayes, who did aſſay by the authoritative ſentence of a Magiſtrate or Miniſter to force their parents conſent to their marriage. As for the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners addition of the Miniſters compelling parents to give portions to their children, that the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath any ſuch cannon or practiſe, its an impudent lye; but in the place alledged is a paſſage againſt the ſparing of the life of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, contrary to the Law of God: and for the excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of Adulterers, when by the negligence of the Magiſtrate their life is ſpared, this poſſibly may be the thorne in the ſide of ſome which makes them bite and ſpurne with the heele ſo furio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſly againſt the Authors and lovers of ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere a diſcipline.</p>
            <p>The Presbyteries next injury is done to the Lawyers; Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, and other Eccleſiaſtick Courts revoke their Sentences. Anſ. No ſuch matter ever was attempted in <hi>Scotland;</hi> fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent prohibitions have beene obtained by curtiſan Biſhops againſt the higheſt civill judicatories in <hi>England;</hi> but that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Presbytery or Synode in <hi>Scotland</hi> did ſo much as aſſay to impede or repeale the proceedings of any the meaneſt ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Court, I did never heare it ſo much as alledged by our adverſaries.<note place="margin">Serious cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing is no Epiſcpall crime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The next injurie is againſt all Maſters, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtreſſes of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, whom the Presbytery will have to be perſonally exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in their knowledge once a yeare, and to be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, if groſly and willfully ignorant. Anſw. If it be a crime for a Miniſter to call together parcels of his congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:110929:36"/> to be inſtructed in the grounds of Religion, that ſervants and children and (where ignorance is ſuſpected,) others alſo may be tryed in their knowledge of the Catechiſme; or if it be a crime that in family-viſitations oftener then once a yeare the converſation of every member of the Church may be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked upon; we confeſſe the Miniſters of Scotland were guilty thereof, and ſo farre as we know the generality of the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall faction may purge themſelves by oath of any ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion: for they had ſomewhat elſe to doe, then to be at the paines of inſtructing or trying the Spirituall State of every ſheep in their flocks: we confeſſe likewiſe, that it is both our order and practiſe to keepe off from the holy table, whom we finde groſly and wilfully ignorant: but that ever any for ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ignorance was excommunicate in Scotland,<note place="margin">Church ſeſſions are not high commiſſiones</note> none who knowes us will affirme it.</p>
            <p>The laſt whom he will have to be wronged by the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te y are the common people, who muſt groane under a high commiſſion in every pariſh, where ignorant governors rule all without Law, medling even in domeſticall jarres betwixt man and wife, Maſter and Servant. Anſw. This is but a gybe of revenge for the overthrow of their Tyrannous high Commiſſion-Court, where they were wont to play the Rex at their pleaſure above the higheſt ſubjects of the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and would never give over that their inſolent domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering court, till the King and Parliaments of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes did agree to throw it downe about their eares. The thing he je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es at, is the congregationall Elderſhip, a j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory which all the Reformed doen joy to their great comfort as much as S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otland. They are farre from all arbitrary ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications; their Lawes are the holy Scripture and acts of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Church j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dicatories, which rule ſo clearely the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gniſance, that rarely any difficulty remaines therein: or if it doe, immediately by ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rence or appeale it is tranſmitted to the Claſſes or Synode. The judges in the loweſt Elderſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> (as we have ſaid before) are a dozen at leaſt, of the moſt able and pious who can be had in a whole congregation to joyne with the Paſtors one or more as they fall to be: but the Epiſcopall way is to have no diſcipline at
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110929:36"/> all in any congregation: only where there is hope of a fine, the Biſhops officiall will ſummon before his own learned and conſcientious wiſedome, who ever within the whole dioces have fallen into ſuch a fault as he pleaſeth to take notice of: as for domiſtick infirmities, Presbyterians are moſt tender to meddle therein; they come never before any judicatory, but both where the fault is great, and the ſcandal thereof flagrant, and broken out beyond the wals of the family.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the great iniuries and hurts which the Church diſcipline has procured to all orders of men in the whole refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med world, when Epiſcopacy has been ſuch an innocent lambe, or rather ſo holy an Angell upon earth, that no harme at all has ever come by it to any mortall creature: a misbeleeving Jew will nothing misdoubt this ſo evident a truth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. ULT.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Warners exceptions againſt the Covenant are full of confidence, but exceeding frivolous.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THough in the former Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pters the Warner has ſpewed out more venome and gall then the bagge of any one mans ſtomack could have beene ſuppoſed capable of, yet as if he were but beginning to vomite, in this laſt Chapter of the covenant a new flood of blackes poyſon rusheth out of his penne. His undertaking is great, to demonſtrate cleer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y that the covenant is meerly void wicked and impious. His fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt clear demonſtration is, that it was deviſed by ſtrangers, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by ſubjects who wanted requiſite power, and was extorted by juſt feare of unjuſt ſuffering, ſo that many that tooke it with their lips, never conſented with their hearts. Anſ. This cleer demonſtration is but a poore and evill argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the Major, if it were put in forme, would hardly be granted, but I ſtand on the minor as weake and falſe; for the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:110929:37"/> Covenant was not deviſed by ſtrangers;<note place="margin">The Covenant was not diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</note> the Commiſſioners of the Parliament of England, together with the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Parliament and generall aſſembly of Scotland were the firſt and onely framers thereof, but they who gave the life and being to it in England were the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parliament at Weſtminſter by the Kings call, and at that time acknowledged by his Majeſtie without any queſtion about the lawfulneſſe of their conſtitution and authority: theſe men and that Court were not I hope great ſtrangers in England. The Covenant was not impoſed upon the King: but the Parliament of both Kingdomes, made it their earneſt deſire unto his Majeſtie, that he would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to joyne with them in that Covenant, which they did judge to be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine peece of their ſecurity for their Religion and liberties in all the three Kingdomes. As for their impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it upon the ſubjects of England, an ordinance of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (though the King conſent not) by the uncontrover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lawes of England, is a ſufficient authority to crave obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all the ſubjects of England, during the continuance of that Parliament.</p>
            <p>The laſt part of the demonſtration is dishonourable indeed to the Engliſh Nation, if it were true it was no diſhonour to England to joyne with their brethren of Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tland in a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for maintainance of their Religion and Liberties: but for many of the Engliſh to ſweare a Covenant with their lippes, from which their heart did diſſent, and upon this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of heart and mouth to plead the nullity of the Oath, and to advance this plea ſo high as to cleer demonſtration, this is ſuch a diſhonour and diſhoneſty, that a greater can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fall upon a man of reputed integrity; eſpecically when the ground of the lye and pe ju y is n evident falshood: for the Covenant was not extorted from any fleſh in England by feare of any unjuſt ſuffering; ſo far w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s it from this, that to this day it could never be obtained from the Parliament of England, to enjoyne that Covenant upon any by the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a two pence.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:110929:37"/>
            <p>The Warners ſecond demonſtration is no better then the firſt; the ground of it is,<note place="margin">Covenanters were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but underſtood what they ſware.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat all oathes are void which have deceipt and errour of the ſubſtantiall conditions incident to them. This ground had need to be much better cautioned, then here it is, before it can ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd for a major of a clear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration; but how is the minor proved? behold how much ſhort the Warners proofes are of his great boaſtings. His firſt argument is grounded upon an evident falſhood, that in the Covenant we ſweare the lately deviſed diſcipline to be Chriſts inſtitution. <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is no ſuch word nor any ſuch matter in all the Covenant: was the Warners ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred ſo great againſt that peece of write, that being to make cleare demonſtrations againſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he would not ſo much as caſt his eye upon that which he was to oppugne, Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſweare, to endeavour the reformation of England, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of God and the beſt reformed Churches, but not a word of the Scots Presbytery, nor of any thing in any Church even the beſt reformed, unleſſe it be found accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the paterne of Gods holy word.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ground of his demonſtration is alſo an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent errour,<note place="margin">The Warner unwittingly commends the Covenant.</note> that the covenant in hand is one and the ſame with that of King <hi>James. Anſw.</hi> Such a fancy came never in the head of any man, I know; much leſſe was it ever wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or ſpoken by any, that the Covenant of King <hi>James</hi> in Scotla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d 1580, ſhould be one and the ſame with the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of all the three Kingdomes 1643, whatſoever iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit es may appeare in the matter and ſimilitude in the ends of both; but the groſſeſt errors are ſolide enough grounds for praelaticall clear demonſtrations. Yet here the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner underſtands not how hee is cutting his owne veines; his friends in Scotland will give him ſmall thanks for at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing unto the nationall Covenant of Scotland (that Covenant of King <hi>James</hi>) theſe three properties, that it was iſſued out by the Kings authority, that it was for the maintenance of the Lawes of the realme, and for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the eſtabliſhed Religion: time brings adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to confeſſe of their own accord long denyed truthes. But the Characters; which the Warner in prints upon the ſolemne
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110929:38"/> league and Covenant of the three Kingdomes, wee muſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> pardoned to controvert, till he have taken ſome leaſure to prove his wilde aſſertions. Firſt that the league is againſt the authority of the King; ſecondly that it is againſt the Law; and thirdly that it is fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the overthrow of Religion. The man cannot think, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t any ſhould beleeve his dictats of this kinde without p oofe, ſince the expreſſe words of that league doe flatly contradict him in all theſe three poſitions.</p>
            <p>His gentle memento, that Scotland, when they ſued for aid from the crowne of England, had not the Engliſh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline obtruded upon their Church, might here have beene ſpared; was not the Engliſh diſcipline and liturgy obtruded upon us by the praelats of England with all craft and force? did we ever obtrude our diſciplin upon the Engliſh? but when they of their owne free and long deliberate choice had aboliſhed Biſhops and promiſed to ſet up Presbytery, ſo far as they had found it agreeable to the word of God, were wee not in all reaſon obliged to encourage and aſſiſt them in ſo pious a worke?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The King did not clame the ſole and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lve poſſeſſion of the militia.</note>In the next words the Warner for all his great boaſts fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the weaknes of all the former grounds of his ſecond demonſtration, he offers three new ones: which doubtles will doe the deed: for he avowes poſitively that his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grounds are demonſtrative, yet whoſoever ſhall be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to gripe them with never ſo ſoft an hand ſhall finde them all to be but vanity and winde. The firſt, after a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of proſyllogiſmes reſts upon theſe two foundations, firſt that the right of the <hi>militia</hi> reſides in the King alone: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that by the covenant the <hi>militia</hi> is taken out of the Kings hands; and that every covenanter by his covenant diſpoſes of himſelfe and of his armes, againſt the right which the King hath unto him. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Warner will have much adoe to prove the ſecond ſo, that it may be a ground of a clear demonſtration: but for the firſt, that the power of the <hi>militia</hi> of England doth reſide in the King alone, that the two houſes of Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment have nothing at all to doe with it, and that their taking of armes for the defence of the liberties of England or any other imaginable cauſe againſt my party
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110929:38"/> countenanced by the Kings preſence againſt his lawes muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a together unlawfull; if his demonſtration be no clearer, hen the ground whereupon he builds it, I am ſure, it will not be viſible to any of his oppoſits who are not like to be convinced of open rebellion by his naked aſſertion, upon which alone he layes this his mighty ground. Beleeve it, he had neede to aſſay its reliefe with ſome colour of an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for none of his owne friends will now take it of his hand for an indemonſtrable principle, ſince the King for a long time was willing to acknowledge the Parliaments joynt intereſt in the Militia, yea to put the whole Militia in their hands alone for a good number of yeares to come: ſo farre was his Majeſtie from the thoughts, that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments medling with a part of the Militia, in the time of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent dangers, ſhould be ſo certainly and clearely the crime of rebellion.</p>
            <p>The Warners ſecond demonſtrative ground wee admit without queſtion in the major, that where the matter is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently unlawfull, the oath is not binding; but the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this in the minor is very falſe. All that hee brings to make it appeare to be true, is that the King is the ſupream Legiſlator; that it is unlawfull for the ſubjects of England to change any thing eſtabliſhed by Law, eſpecially to the prejudice of the Praelates without their own conſent, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a third order of the Kingdome; otherwiſe it would be a harder meaſure then the Friers and Abbots received from <hi>Henry</hi> the eight.<note place="margin">The change of lawes in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ordinarily begin by the two houſes w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thout the King.</note> Anſ. May the Warner be pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how farre his dictates here are from all reaſon, much more from evident demonſtrations. That the burden of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and ceremonies was become ſo heavy to all the three Kingdomes, that there was reaſon to endeavour their lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide, he does not offer to diſpute; but all his complaint runnes againſt the manner of their removall: this (ſay I) was done in no other then the ordinary and high path-way, whereby all burdenſome Lawes and cuſtomes uſe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved. Doth not the Houſes of Parliament, firſt begin with their Ordinance before the Kings conſent be ſought to a Law? is not an Ordinance of the Lords and Commons a good war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110929:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:110929:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:110929:40"/> to change a former Law during the ſitting of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? The Lawes and cuſtomes of England permit not the King by his diſſent to ſtoppe that change.<note place="margin">The King did really conſent to the aboliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Biſhops.</note> I grant for the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dinance to a ſtanding Law, the Kings conſent is required, but with what qualifications and exceptions wee need not here to debate, ſince his Majeſties conſent to the preſent caſe of aboliſhing Biſhops was obtained well neere to as farre as was deſired; and what it yet lacking, wee are in a faire way to obtaine it: for the Kings Majeſtie long agoe did agree to the rooting out of Epiſcopacy in Scotland, hee was willing alſo in England and Ireland to put them out of the Parliament, and all civil Courts, and to diveſt them of all civill power, and to joyne with them Presbyteries for Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and ſpirituall jurisdiction; yea, to aboliſh them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally name and thing, not onely for three yeares but ever till he and his Parliament ſhould agree upon ſome ſetled order, for the Church; was not this <hi>Tantamont</hi> to a pertuall aboliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? for all and every one in both houſes, having abjured E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſopacy by ſolemne Oath and Covenant, the Parliament was in no hazard of agreeing with the King to re-erect the fallen chaires of the Biſhops: ſo there remained no other, but that either his Majeſtie ſhould come over to their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or by his not agreeing with them, yet really to agree with them in the perpetuall abolition of Epiſcopacy, ſince the confeſſion was for the laying Biſhops aſide for ever, till hee and his houſes had agreed upon a ſettled order for the Church. If this be not a full and formall enough conſent to the Ordinance of changing the former Lawes anent praelats, his Majeſtie, who now is, eaſily may and readily would ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all ſuch defects: if ſome of the faction did not continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, for their owne evil intereſts, whiſper in his eares per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious counſell, as our Warner in this place alſo doeth by frighting the King in conſcience from any ſuch conſent;<note place="margin">The praelats would fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tter the King into a Tyranny.</note> for this end he caſts out a diſcourſe, the ſinews whereof are in theſe three Epiſcopall maximes Firſt, that the legiſlative power is ſoly in the King, that is according to his Brethrens Commentary, that the Parliament is but the Kings great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of free choyce, without or againſt whoſe votes hee may
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110929:40"/> make or unmake what Lawes he thinkes expedient; but for them to make any Ordinance for changing without his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of any thing that has been, inſtituting any new thing, or for them to defend this their legall right and cuſtome (time out of minde) againſt the armes of the Malignant party, no man may deny it to be plaine rebellion.</p>
            <p n="2">II.<note place="margin">The praelates take to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive voice in Parliament.</note> That the King and Parliament both together cannot make a Law, to the prejudice of Biſhops without their owne conſent, they being the third order of the Kindome: for albeit it be ſacriledge in the Lords and Commons, to claime any the ſmalleſt ſhare of the legiſlative power, (this in them were to pyck the chiefeſt jewel out of the Kings Crowne) yet this muſt be the due priviledge of the Biſhops, they muſt be the third order of the Kingdome, yea the firſt and moſt high of the three, farre above the other two temporall States of Lords and Commons; their ſhare in the Legiſlative power muſt be ſo great, that neither King nor Parliament can paſſe any Law without their conſent, ſo that according to their humble proteſtation, all the Lawes and Acts, which have been made by King and Parliament, ſince they were expelled the houſe of Lords, are cleerly void and null.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt grant that the King and Parliament in diveſting Biſhops of their temporall honour and eſtates,<note place="margin">The praelats grieve that Monks and Friers, the Pope and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals were ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten out of England by <hi>H.</hi>
               </note> in aboliſhing their places in the Church, doe ſin more againſt conſcience then did <hi>Henry</hi> the eight and his Paliament, when they put down the Abbots and the Friers. We muſt beleeve that <hi>Henry</hi> the eight his aboliſhing the order of Monks was one of the acts of his greateſt Tyranny and greed: we muſt not doubt, but according to Law and reaſon, Abbots and Priours ought to have kept ſtill their vote in Parliament, that the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteryes and Nunryes ſhould have ſtood in their integrity, that the King and Parliament did wrong in caſting them downe, and that now they ought in conſcience to be ſet up againe, yea, that <hi>Henry</hi> the eight againſt all reaſon and conſcience did renounce his due obedience to the Pope, the Patriarch of the Weſt, the firſt Biſhop of the univerſe, to whom the ſuperinſpection and government of the whole Catholick Church in all reaſon doth belong. Though all
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110929:41"/> this be here glaunced at by the Warner, and elſewhere wee prove it to be the declared mind of his Brethren, yet we muſt be pardoned not to accept them, as undenyable princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ples of cleare demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The juſt ſupre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macy of Kings is not prejud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Covenant.</note>The laſt ground of the Doctors demonſtration, is, that the Covenant is an Oath to ſet up the Presbyterian govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in England, as it is in Scotland, &amp; that this is contrary to the Oath of Supremacy; for the Oath of Supremacy makes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the onely ſupreame head and Governour of the Church of England, that is, the civill head to ſee that every man doe his duty in his calling; alſo it gives the King a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame power over all perſons in all cauſes: but the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery is a Politicall Papacie, acknowledging no governour but only the Presbyters: it gives the King power over all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as Subjects, but none at all in Eccleſiaſtick cauſes. Anſ. Is there in all this reaſoning any thing ſound? Firſt, what article of the Covenant beares the ſetting up of the Presbyterian government in England as it is in Scotland? II. If the Oath of ſupremacy import no more then what the Warners expreſſe words are here, that the King is a civill head, to ſee every man doe his duty in his calling, let him be aſſured that no Presbyterian in Scotland was ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that ſupremacy. III. That the Presbytery is a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, and that a politicall one, the Warner knowes it ought not to be granted upon his bare word. IV. That In Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land no other governors are acknowledged then Presbyters, himſelfe contradicts in the very next words, where hee tells that the Scots Presbytery aſcribs to the King a power over all perſons as ſubjects. V. That any Presbyterian in Scotland makes it ſacriledge to give the King any power at all in any Eccleſiaſtick cauſe,<note place="margin">The Warner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inſolent Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> it is a ſenſeleſſe untruth.</p>
            <p>The Warners arguments are not more idle and weake, then his triumphing upon them is inſolent: for he concludes from theſe wife and ſtrong demonſtrations, that the poore covenant is apparently deceitfull, unvalide, impious, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, and what not? yea, that all the learned divines in Europe will conclude it ſo, &amp; that all the Covenanters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves who have any ingenuity, muſt grant thus much; and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110929:41"/> that no knowing Engliſh man can deny it, but his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will give him the lie. Anſw. If the Warner with any ſeriouſneſſe hath weighed this part of his own write, and if his minde go along with his pen, I may without great preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion pronounce his judgement to be none of the moſt ſolide.</p>
            <p>His following vapours being full of aire we let them eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh; only while he mentioneth our charging the King with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of changing the Religion and government, we anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that we have been moſt willing alwaies to aſcribe to the King good intentions, but withall we have long avowed that the praelaticall party have gone beyond intentions to manifeſt by printed declarations and publick actions their formed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne to bring Tyranny upon the States, and popery upon the Churches of all the three Kingdomes, and that this very write of the Warners makes it evident, that this ſame minde yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines within them without the leaſt ſhew of repentance. So long as the conſcience of the court is mannaged by men of ſuch principles, it is not poſſible to free the hearts of the moſt underſtanding from a great deale of Jealouſly and feare to have Religion and lawes ſtill overturned by that faction.</p>
            <p>But the Wa ner commands us, to ſpeake to his <hi>Dilemma,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The covenant is not for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating of Religion by armes.</note> whither we thinke it lawfull or unlawfull for ſubjects to take armes againſt their prince meerely for Religion? We anſwer, that the reaſons whereby he thinks to conclude againſt us, on both ſides are very poor. If we ſhall ſay, it is unlawfull, then he makes us to condemne our ſelves, becauſe our covenant teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies to the world, that we have taken up armes meerly to alter Religion, and that we beare no alleagiance to our King but in order to Religion, which in plaine terms is to our own hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and conceits. <hi>Anſ.</hi> There be many untruths here in few words; firſt how much reality and truth the Warner and ſome of his fellowes beleeves to be in that thing which they call Religion, their own heart knownes; but it can be no great cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in him to make the Religion of all covenanters to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their own humours and conceits. Secondly it is not true that Covenanters beare no alleagiance to the King but only in order to Religion. III. The Parliament of England denied that they took u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> armes againſt their King, though to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110929:42"/> defend themſelves againſt the popiſh pralaticall and malignant faction, who were about to deſtroy them with armes. IV. They have declared, that their purpoſe was not at all, to alter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion but to purge it from the corruption of Biſhops and ceremonies that too long had beene noxious unto them. V. They have oft profeſſed that their rames were taken for the defence of their juſt liberties, whereof the preſervation and reformation of Religion was but one.</p>
            <p>The other horne of his <hi>Dilemma</hi> is as blunt in puſhing as the former. If we make it lawfull (ſaith he) to take up armes for Religion, we then juſtifie the independents and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts; wee make way for any that will plant what ever they apprehend to be true Religion by force, and to cut the throat of all Magiſtrates, who are in a contrary opinion to them; that it is a ridiculous partiality for any to priviledge their owne Religion as truth and Goſpell.<note place="margin">The Warners black Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme.</note> Anſw. Whether will theſe men go at laſt? the ſtrength of this reaſon is black atheiſme, that there is no realty of truth in any Religion, that no man may be permitted to take his Religion for any thing more but his owne apprehenſion, which without ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous folly he muſt not preferre to any other mans appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of a contrary Religion; this is much worſe then the pagane Scepticiſme, which turned all reality of truth into a meer apprehenſion of truth, wherein their was no certainty at all: this not onely turnes the moſt certaine truths, even theſe divine ones of Religion, into meer uncertaine concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but which is worſe, it will have the moſt orthodoxe beleever ſo to think, ſpeake and act, as if the opinions of Independents, Anabaptiſts, Turks, Jewes, Pagans or groſſe Atheiſts were as good, true and ſolide as the beleefe of <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Paul</hi> were of the truths revealed to them from heaven. Secondly we ſay that ſubiects defence of their Religion and liberties eſtabliſhed by Law, againſt the violent uſurpation of Papiſts, Prelats or Malignants, is not the planting of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by armes; much leſſe is it the cutting of the throats of all Magiſtrates, who differ in any point of Religion.<note n="*" place="margin">The Praelats condemne the defenſive armes of the Dutch and French Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</note> III. In the Iudgement of the prelaticall party, the defenſive armes of the Proteſtants in <hi>France, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> muſt be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110929:42"/> as much condemned as the offenſive armes of the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts in <hi>Munſter,</hi> or of the ſectaries this day in <hi>England.</hi> Can theſe men dreame that the World for their pleaſure will ſo farre diveſt themſelves of all Religion and reaſon, as to take from their hande ſo brutiſh and Atheiſticall maximes.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Praelats decline the judgement of counſels. The Praelats overthrow of the foundation of Proteſtant Religion.</note>He concludes with a wiſh of a generall councell, at leaſt of all proteſtant Churches for to condemne all breachers of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious principles. Anſ. All true covenanters goe before him in that deſire, being confident that he and his fellowes as they have declined already the moſt ſolemne aſſemblies of their own countries, upon aſſurance of their condemnation, ſo their tergiverſation would be as great if they were to anſwer to an oecumenick Synod. What (I pray) would the Warner ſay in a councell of proteſtant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the practiſe of his party pointed at in his laſt words? I meane their purging the Pope of <hi>Antichriſtianiſme,</hi> of purpoſe to make way for a reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, yea for a returne to <hi>Rome,</hi> as this day it lyes under the wings of the Pope and Cardinals.<note n="*" place="margin">The Praelats are ſtill pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory to deſtroy the King and all his Kingdomes if they may not be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> Alſo what could they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in a Chriſtian councel unto this charge, which is the drift of this whole Book, that they are ſo farre from any remorſe for all the blood and miſery, which their wickedneſſe (moſt) has brought on the former King and all his Kingdomes theſe eleven yeares, that rather then they had not the Covenant and generall aſſembly in Scotland deſtroyed as an Idol and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, they will chuſe yet ſtill to imbroyle all in new cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities? This King alſo and his whole Family, the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the blood and Eſtates in all the three Kingdoms, muſt be hazarded for the ſowing together of the torne mytres, and the rejecting of the fallen chayres of Praelats. If Biſhops muſt lie ſtil, in their deſerved ruines, they perſevere in their perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory reſolution, to have their burials ſprinckled with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of the royall Family and all the three Kingdomes,</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
